<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new dialogue vvherin is conteyned the examinatio[n] of the messe and of that kynde of priesthode, whych is ordeined to saye messe: and to offer vp for remyssyon of synne, the body and bloud of Christe agayne.</title>
            <author>Turner, William, d. 1568.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14057</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24363</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108032</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843722</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843722</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8474</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14057)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8474)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 450:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new dialogue vvherin is conteyned the examinatio[n] of the messe and of that kynde of priesthode, whych is ordeined to saye messe: and to offer vp for remyssyon of synne, the body and bloud of Christe agayne.</title>
                  <author>Turner, William, d. 1568.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[104] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1548]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By William Turner.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F G⁴ (G4 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8474:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8474:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A new Dialogue <hi>VVHEREIN IS CONTEY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> the examination of the Meſſe, and of that kynde of Preiſthode, whych is ordeined to ſay meſſe: and to offer vp for remyſſyon of ſynne, the bodye and bloude of Chriſte agayne.</p>
            <p>Beleue not euery ſpirite, but trye the ſpirites, whether they be of God or no: for many falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes are gone into the worlde.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:8474:2"/>
            <head>The names of the ſpeakers in thys Dialogue.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Maſtres Miſſa</item>
               <item>Maſter Knowlege</item>
               <item>Maſter Fremouthe</item>
               <item>Maſter iuſtice of Peace</item>
               <item>Peter preco the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry</item>
               <item>Palemon the Iudge</item>
               <item>Doctor Prophyri</item>
               <item>Syr Phillyp Philargyry</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8474:2"/>
            <head>VVYLLYAM TVR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NER VNTO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LTHOVGHE IT BE not belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gyng vnto my</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to diſpute of maters of diuinite, whyche am a Phiſitian: yet extreme ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſite requiri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to do in thys kynde of war, as coblers, ſhoma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kers, maſons, carpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ters, &amp; al other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of handy occupations are compelled to doo, when theyr cytie is beſeged, to take wepens in theyr handes and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come warriers, whych haue had lytle or no experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of war before, when as theyr cytie is beſeged. Whych: yf that (when a cyty is beſeged) euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is a faythfull citizen oughte to do the beſte that he can, to defende hys cytye, and to ouercu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the enemies of the ſame: who wyll blame me, which am no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of diuinitie, when as the cyty of God, whereof I am a ſworne Citizen,
<pb facs="tcp:8474:3"/> is beſeged, wyth ſo great hoſtes of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſhe warriers: yf I play in this tyme of nede, the diuine warryer, to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the forſayd cyty, and endeuore my ſelfe to ouercome the enemyes of the ſame. The enemies of our city, ar they, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che take by viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly and neceſſarie ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of our cyty and would by force thurſt into our cyty, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of theyr awn maki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ttary vnto the lawes of our lawmaker which buil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded our city, &amp; dyed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liberty of the ſame. Suche enemyes, ar the Byſhop of Rome, and all Popyſhe Prelates and preiſtes, whyche mangle and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe, yea, rob and many wayes deface the mooſte comfortable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſeale of our ſaluation and redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the holy Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſtes body &amp; bloude, and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtede of the ſame, ſet in a mere mannes inuention, a certayne Popiſh playe, whych they call the meritorius Meſſe, bearyng vs in hande that, that they can doo wyth it as muche as our redemer Chriſt coulde do w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys moſt
<pb facs="tcp:8474:3"/> bleſſed paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which thyng I iudge to be greatly to the dyſhonour of Chriſt, that is that our moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeal of our lybertie, and redemption, ſhould be ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gled and robbed, and for the moſte parte of the hole yere, taken from vs, and that the worke of a man ſhould be made equall with the worke of our Lorde and lawmaker whych is both God and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I could do no leſſe, but wryte thys booke, to defende the bleſſed ordynaunce of our Lorde and redemer, and wraſtle a lytle wyth the wycked mannes ordynau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, to helpe to dryue them out of the churche oure cytie, and to reſtore the ordynaunce of our ſauyour into the church agayn. I know that many wyll be offended, and take it very greuouſly, that I ſhoulde wryts of thys matter, and I loke for none other, but ſome ſhal cal me knaue and heretyke for my laboure taken in thys matter. Some wyll there be alſo of Sathans ſyde, whyche neuer can be ſatiate wyth bloud, whych wyll de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre
<pb facs="tcp:8474:4"/> to haue my bloude, as dyuers in Englande, at thys daye, yet lyuynge haue done, God forgiue them. And the ſame, yf that theyr crueltyes were not repreſſed and holden downe wyth the hyer powers, whych ar manteyners of al truth and honeſty, would not leaue alyue in thys realme one of my iuge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe ether to wryte or to preach agaynſt ſuch ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes inuencions, as at thys tyme, I do wryte agaynſt: but I care not for theſe horſleches, truſtynge that he that hath ſo ofte delyuered me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the handes of myne enemies, wyll either ſaue me from them at this tyme alſo, or elles, yf it be hys pleaſure that I ſhal loſe my lyfe for his names ſake, I ſhall be ſure to fynde it agayn. But yf there be any man that of a conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce had agaynſte me and thynke that I holde any falſe opinions in thys boke or any other booke and woulde haue the amendement of me and not my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction yf they be learned, let them wryte agaynſte me, and I ſhal anſwer
<pb facs="tcp:8474:4"/> them or elles yf I can not, recante it that I haue wrytten. In the meane ſeaſon I woulde deſyre the vnlearned whyche erre by reaſon of ignoraunce and not of malyce, that they woulde ceaſe from raylynge agaynſte me, tyll that theyr chefe champions haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed my booke, and haue perceyued that I wyll not recante. Thys would I alſo requyre of learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yf it coul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be obteyned. I anſwered wythin theſe ſeuen yeres a certayne learned man of Englande and confuted as well as I could, hys boke but he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto all honeſtie and learnyng, perceyuynge that he was not able to anſwere to my booke, in euery booke that he wrote afterwardes agaynſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men rayled and ſcoffed agaynſte me by name. Should learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> play ſuche partes in a chryſten kingdom? I thinke that it were mete that he that is learned &amp; ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly in wryti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or in pulpit ſpeaketh agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld ether be
<pb facs="tcp:8474:5"/> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to confute hys opinions that he rayleth agaynſt, or elles ſhould be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled openly to cry hym mercy, whom he hathe ſklaundered. Yf thys were brought to paſſe, we ſhold haue fewer raylers in Englande then we haue.</p>
            <p>Therfore haue I ſette my name vnto thys boke that yf thou thynke that I haue wrytten herein, any thynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt God or hys word, thou mayeſt knowe to whome thou ſhouldeſte wryte. Almyghty God graunte to the ignorante, knowlege, and to them that haue knowledge, to lyue thereafter. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="tcp:8474:5"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Maſtres Miſſa.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am credible informed by the reporte of my faythful and vnfayned fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, that there ar nowadayes many raſh &amp; vngodly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which vtterly deſpice me, &amp; ſet me at nought. ſaiynge, that I am not ſhe that I am take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for, &amp; that I am y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Popis dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and haue dryuen out of the church, the ſupper of oure Lorde, and haue ſet vp my ſelfe, in the ſtede of it: and that I am y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt blaſphemy, that euer was vnto Chriſtes death and paſſion, wyth many other ſpitefull lyes &amp; ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, wherwyth they woulde kyll me, yf they coulde. But, ye good catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke and Chriſten people, knowe well enoughe, what I am and from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce I came? Ye wote that I came from Chriſte and hys Apoſtles, and that I am allowed &amp; approued wyth mo, then an hundreth holy fathers Byſhoppes of Rome, and I haue bene more, then theſe .CCCCC. yeres approued by
<pb facs="tcp:8474:6"/> the hole churche. And becauſe manye newe fangled fellowes, would that I ſhoulde be remoued oute of the way, that Chryſtes ſupper, (as they call it) myghte haue place in the Churche, as an holoſmmer thyng and more profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for mannes ſoule then I am: I wyll at thys tyme (compelled by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſytie,) compare my ſelfe wyth theyr ſupper, and proue my ſelfe more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of place in Chriſtes churche, then it is.</p>
               <p>The Supper that theſe fellowes ſpeake af, euen after theyr awne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon, is but a memoryall of Chryſtes death, of a gyuyng of thankes, for the benefit of mans ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherby ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fayth is ſtrengthened, and theyr loue is in creaſed. Theſe are the chefeſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, that theſe new goſpellers doo gyue vnto theyr ſo greatly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended ſupper. But harke now what I both do and ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do. I deliuer the ſely ſoules that haue bene long pituoſſly puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in purgatory, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr paynes and
<pb facs="tcp:8474:6"/> tormentes. Where fynde you in al the hole Scrypture, that the ſupper of oure Lorde, can doo ſo muche? I can make fayre wether, and rayne: I can heale all Syckneſſes, and brynge dampned ſoules oute of Hell: I can purchaſſe remyſſyon of ſynnes, by the offerynge vp agayne, of Chryſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloude. I can wyth fyue wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, make bothe God and man. Why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thynge, ſeynge that God can not doo: can not I do more, then God can doo? Nowe lette theſe newe fellowes tell, whether the ſupper of our Lordes, can do ſo much or no. Yet for all this, yf nede requyre, I ſaye, that I am the ſupper of our Lord: and my great fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Prophiry my patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doctor of the Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> law, &amp; ſyr Phillip Philargiry, doctor of diuinite, haue taught me to call my ſelfe ſo: yf that my other name, ſhoulde be at any tyme to odyous. <hi>Ite miſſa eſt:</hi> fare ye wel, tyl y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nexte tyme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we mete again.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Knouule.</speaker>
               <p>here ye not, as this woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeketh ſo blaſphemouſſly
<pb facs="tcp:8474:7"/> agaynſte God and his worde? Marke ye not, as ſhe preferreth her ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſupper of our lord Ieſu chriſt and yet ſhe is the Popis doughter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fremouth.</speaker>
               <p>I heare her talke very wel howbeit I perceyue not the haynouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the matter, as ye doo: therfore, ſhew me it playnly &amp; I ſhall not ſpare to lay it to her charge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Knouulege.</speaker>
               <p>fyrſt when ſhe is but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> creature of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhe ſayeth, that ſhe can take ſynne awaye, by the offerynge vp of Chriſtes bodye and bloude: wherein, ſhe maketh her ſelfe equall wyth our ſauyour Chriſt. And wher as ſhe ſayeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make rayn &amp; fayre wether, &amp; heale all maner of dyſeaſes, ſhe makethe her ſelfe god: Where as ſhe ſayeth, that ſhe ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make wyth .v. wordes, bothe God and man, ſhe maketh her ſelfe myghtyer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god for ſeyng that god is euerlaſtyng, and hath no begynnynge, he can not make hym ſelfe then wher as ſhe ſayeth, that ſhe maketh God ſhe makethe her ſelfe myghtier the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god. Yf this be not blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy,
<pb facs="tcp:8474:7"/> what ſhall we call blaſphemy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fremouth.</speaker>
               <p>Syr, theſe are intollerable blaſphemies in dede, therfore, ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hal not ſcape wyth them thus, How Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telwoman tary a lytle, and heare what ſhallbe ſayde vnto you. Here maſter Iuſtice before al thys worſhypful co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, in God and the Kynges name I charge you wyth thys woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſhe may be furthcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng, to anſwer vnto ſuch crymes of hereſy and blaſphemy, as ſhallbe layde vnto her charge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Maſter Iuſtice.</speaker>
               <p>Woteſt thou, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lewed fellow what thou ſayeſt &amp; doeſt? wylt thou rayle agaynſte the holy &amp; bleſſed meſſe, and accuſe her of hereſy &amp; blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy? lay ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des on this felow, for he ſpeaketh againſt the ſyxe articles, and agaynſt the Sacramente of the altar. I take wytnes of you neyghboures, what thys fellowe ſayeth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouulege.</speaker>
               <p>Soft ſyr and be not ſo haſty, yf that ye put thys man in pryſon, and refuſe to execute it, that he hathe charged you wyth all ſaye not but ye be warned ye
<pb facs="tcp:8474:8"/> wyl be throw your ſelfe. Ye ar begiled maſter Iuſtice, the worlde is not now as ye thinke it is. The time of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the profeſſors of the truth (tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes be vnto God) beginneth now to weare away, ye haue perſecuted long enough already in tyme paſt, &amp; a lytle to longe. The kynges intent &amp; purpos, is nowe at the beginning of his reygne to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge and clenſe the churche of al abuſes and enormites, &amp; to examine and try with the touch ſtone of goddes word, all ſacrifices &amp; ceremonyes, whych are in the church: whether thei ar agreing wyth the word of God or no: that they that do agre, may be allowed &amp; holden ſtyl, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei, that ar diſagreing, may be taken away. Then ſeyng that thys is the Kynges mooſte godly purpoſe, when as ye wyll not ſuffer men to cite abuſes &amp; ſuch thynges, as at thought to be abuſes, to come to examination, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may gather playnly, that ye ente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to reſyſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges moſt godly purpos. Which yf ye doo, ye ar not his frende.
<pb facs="tcp:8474:8"/> Yf the meſſe, after dew examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be found to be good &amp; godly ſhe ſhal haue no harme, but yf ſhe be ſounde to be of anticſtrih &amp; but a fained thyng, to wyn money w<hi rend="sup">c</hi>, to the ydle preſtes tht ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not preach: why may not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingaes hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes as well put her down, &amp; dryue her out of the church, as the popes wilines ſet her vp, and broughte her into the church? Therfore I wil aduyſe you, to leaue of your troblynge of thys honeſt man, &amp; be contet, to execute his reſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble requeſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Maſter Iuſtic.</speaker>
               <p>Syr, at your inſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, I wyll let this man go, &amp; wyl alſo ſe, that thys woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall be furth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, to anſwer vnto ſuch thynges as ſhal be layde vnto her charge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uuleg.</speaker>
               <p>Farewel maſter Iuſtice.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. Iuſt.</speaker>
               <p>farewell ſyr.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Palemon the Iudge.</speaker>
               <p>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quere Peter, yf there be any man that hathe any actyon, or matter, to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of thys daye in thys Courte, lette hym brynge it in, and entre it and he ſhall be hearde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peter Preco.</speaker>
               <p>Yf there be anye, that hath any mater
<pb facs="tcp:8474:9"/> in thys courte, let him entre hys actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for my Lord iudge is redy to heate it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>M. Fremouth.</speaker>
               <p>Here is a woman (my Lorde) whyche defendeth open hereſy, and commytteth blaſphemy agaynſte God &amp; his holy word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Palemon.</speaker>
               <p>What ſayeſt thou woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is it ſo, as thys ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hathe reported of thee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miſſa.</speaker>
               <p>I deny, that I ſpake any hereſy, or commytted any blaſphemy in al my life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fremouth</speaker>
               <p>Dyddeſt thou not ſaye, that y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> cameſte fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt and the Apoſtles: that thou couldeſt delyuer ſoules out of purga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tory, yea, and dampned ſoules oute of hel, and couldeſt purcheſſe forgiuenes of ſynnes, wyth the offerynge vp of Chriſtes body and bloude agayn, and that thou couldeſt do more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt can do? are not theſe ſaiynges ful of hereſy and blaſphemy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miſſa</speaker>
               <p>I grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te I ſayd all the ſaiynges whych ye haue reherſed ſauinge the laſt whych I vt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terly deny that I euer ſaid or though in all my lyfe tyme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fremouth.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall proue my Lorde) er I go hence, by her
<pb facs="tcp:8474:9"/> awn ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de wrytyng, that ſhe taketh in hande to doo, that God neuer toke in hande, that is, to make God, whych yf I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhew, I ſhall proue, that ſhe hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that ſhe can do more then Chriſt can do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Palemon.</speaker>
               <p>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye deny not, but that ye tayde all the reſte, whereof ye are accuſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Miſſa.</speaker>
               <p>I ſayde them, and wyll ſay them agayne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouulege.</speaker>
               <p>And thoſe ſaiynges ſhall I, by the helpe of God proue falſe, Hereticall and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphirꝰ and Philargirꝰ.</speaker>
               <p>We deſyre you (my Lorde) that ye wyll ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myt vs to be defenders and aduocates vnto thys innocent woman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Palemon.</speaker>
               <p>I am well content, defende her as well as ye can.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Prophiry.</speaker>
               <p>Euen as it is ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſemynge nor godly that the holy ſcripture ſhould be called to examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and tryal, whether it be ſcripture or no, &amp; they that holde that ſcrypture is no ſcripture ought ſtreyght wayes to be taken for Heretikes and infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les: ſo the bleſſed and holy Meſſe why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is as true as the ſcripture is and
<pb facs="tcp:8474:10"/> came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, as well as the ſcripture came, ought not to be ſuffered to com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnto any examination or tryal: and a they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doubt or holde agaynſt it, ough by and by to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for Heretikes and infideles. The bleſſed meſſe is ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hygh and inſcrutable miſtery, that n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lay man ought to reſon or diſpute of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> And though ther were any abuſe crep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into the Miſſe (as no man is hable to proue that there is any at all) it ſhould belong only vnto the Byſhoppes and vnto the clergy, to medle wyth ſuche matters, and not to ſuche lay and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned fellowes, as theſe be. Whych as it dothe appere by theyr apparell haue neyther taken any degre in diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, neyther in the Cannon law. Cat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the wyſe man ſayeth to ſuche. <hi>Mitte ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chana dei:</hi> let the ſecretes of God alon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> And Salomon ſayeth: He that is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſercher of Goddes maieſty, ſhall be ouerthrowen wyth hys glorye. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not lawfull that theſe fello<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uee ſhould mydle wyth any ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb facs="tcp:8474:10"/> as the meſſe is. Moreouer, yf theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s accuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be allowed, ther is no ſuche holy ceremonie in the hole church, whiche ſhoulde not come into great ieoperdy of deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſone after. Let al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beware, that they breake not a good ordre. Now is the churche in a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight good ordre, which yf it were ones broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the church ſhould come in great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eoperdy. Take but one ſtaffe out of a bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>del, ar not al the reſt looſe &amp; ready to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all out? the ceremonies of the church, ar knyt in ſuch an ordre, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf ye take one away, that al the reſt ſhal be in ieoꝑdy of fallynge into deſtruction. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, ye know alſo that the multitude of thys realme, hath the meſſe in ſuche reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and taketh it for ſuch a godly thynge (as they are bounde to doo no leſſe) yf they ſhoulde ones perceyue that the Meſſe ſhoulde be handeled as a thefe and a robber, that is, yf ſhe ſhoulde be openlye accuſed befo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the face of the Courte, the rude people woulde make an inſurrectyon,
<pb facs="tcp:8474:11"/> and ſo ſhould all thys realme come in great ieoperdy, by the breakyng of the inwarde peace, of oure foren enemies. Therfore it were beſte to refuſe theſe mennes accuſation, &amp; not to admyt it, but to punyſh them for theyr bolde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpryſe: But yf ye wyll nedes admyt theyr accuſation, by your pacience, my lord, ſeing that thys is a ſpiritual ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: it ſhoulde be hearde before a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual iudge: for as ariſtotel ſaieth euery man can iudge well in that thyng that he knoweth: then he that knoweth not the matter, can neuer iudge well in it. Wherfore is were beſte that eyther ye ſhould (my Lorde) reiect theſe mennes accuſation or elles ſuffer the matter to be deuolued vnto ſom ſpiritual iudge</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Palemon</speaker>
               <p>the ſaiynges alleged oute of Cato and Salomon forbyd not Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten men to ſearche the ſecretes of thyr fathers teſtament and wyll, whych he hath left in wrytyng, that they ſhould knowe but only ſuche ſecretes, as god hath not opened in hys holy word and
<pb facs="tcp:8474:11"/> teſtamente, and are not neceſſarye for man to know: then theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may reade and ſearche out al the ſecretes, that are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned in the ſcripture, &amp; for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandyng of it, may wyth ſobrenes and diſcretion reſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and confer of anye place of ſcrypture. And yf any thynge be taken for a parte of goddes wyll or commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whych they doubt of, whether it be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined in theyr fathers wyll or no: why maye not they haue a recourſe thyther, to ſe whither it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned ther, or no? Yf that onely Prei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſhoulde be ſuffered to come vnto the readyng of our fathers teſtament, yf they ſayde that the Pope were heed of Chriſtes churche, and all our good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are layme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were theyres at theyr pleaſure: yf we myght not be ſuffered, to ſearche our fathers wyll and teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, whether it were ſo or no: we ſhold haue ſhortly many ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke &amp; rich papiſtes in thys realme, as we haue all redy a great dele to many. And yf they would haue our wyues and doughters alſo,
<pb facs="tcp:8474:12"/> and ſayd, that it were goddes wyl, that we ſhoulde let them haue them, yf we myght not ſearche the teſtament, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it were ſo or no, in what caſe were we in then? As for theſe men, whme ye iudge by theyr apparell to be vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, becauſe they ſeme not too be doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of diuinite, and of the Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> law, and therfore not worthy to accuſe any abuſe, that it may be put away, ye fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low very lytle the ſcripture, whyche ye eyther know or ought to know: <hi>Nolite iudicare ſecundum aſpectum. &amp;c.</hi> Iudge not accordyng vnto the outwarde ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, but iudge after ryght iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The one of theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a maſter of arte of Cambrige, and the other is a maſter of arte of Oxforde, and haue in theyr youth ſtudyed diuinite. Muſte they nowe be vnlearned, becauſe they ar no preiſtes? we ſhall haue a tryal of theyr learnyng hereafter. And though they were as vnlearned as a man is poſſyble: no man can hyndre them to accuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of hereſy &amp; blaſphemy, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they heare ſpeakyng playn blaſphemy
<pb facs="tcp:8474:12"/> and hereſy. Therfore I wil allow their accuſation, &amp; iudge as I ſhall ſe euy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence gyuen. As for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye feate, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf the meſſe ſhould be ſuffered to be ones ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al the ceremonies of the church ſhoulde ſone after decaye and come to nought, it is but a folyſh feare. Yf the meſſe be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de fauty &amp; the ceremonies be founde to be of the ſame ſorte, that the meſſe is, why ſhould they not be al taken away togyther? for thei that are ioyned togyther in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myſcheous dede, ought not to be ſeparated in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentent. Your thondre boltes of vpro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of the people, whereby ye meane that great bloud ſhould be ſhede w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in this realme, yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meſſe ſhould be accu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed of hereſy &amp; blaſphemy, ar but vain for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges moſt louing ſubiectes, ar more godly and wyſer, then they wyll diſturbe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth for the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. What ſay you: yf Baals image were here in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, whiche god commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly to be deſtroyed, and ye knowe certaynly that there ſhoulde aryſe an
<pb facs="tcp:8474:13"/> vprore and the puttyng down of thys Idole: whether were it better to ſuffre the Idol to ſtande ſtyll wyth the hygh diſpleaſure and indygnation of God whych threatned ſubuerſion vnto the lande, where Baal were worſhypped, or to burne Baal wyth an vprore, and ſo to auoyde the indignation of God? I truſt to almyghty god, that we ſhal haue no vprores at all. Where as ye would haue the matter deuolued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome ſpirituall iudge, thynkynge that I am not able to iudge of thys mater, for lacke of knowlege and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng in matters of religion, I would not that ye ſhould reken me to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned in Goddes law, becauſe I am no Biſhop: as though only biſhoppes and prelates were ſpirituall men, and none elles. <hi>Qui non habet ſpiritum dei, hic non eſt eius:</hi> He that hath not the ſpirite of God, he is not hys: But all true Chriſten men haue the ſpirite of God, then are al Chriſten men ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt ye eyther take me for
<pb facs="tcp:8474:13"/> no Chriſten man, or elles graunt, that I am a ſpiritual iuge. As for my kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welege in the holy ſcripture, thoughe many of my predeceſſors haue bene to theyr greate ſhame ſhamefully igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture: I would ye ſhould knowe, that I haue bene brought vp in humanitie, Logike, and diuinitie. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the vniuerſite of Cambryge, tyll I was .xxii. yeres olde, and that ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that tyme, though the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon law hath ben my chefe ſtudy, I haue diligently read the ſcriptures from the begynnyng to the ende, wherby, thankes be vnto the Lorde, thus muche knowlege haue I gotten, that I can diſcerne true religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n from ſuperſtytyon, and knowe my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hepherdes voyce, from a ſtraungers. Thys ſaiyng of Dauid: <hi>Et nunc reges intelligite, &amp; crudimini iudices terre:</hi> Get you vnderſtandyng ye kynges and be you learned ye iudges of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth. This ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce made me reade the ſcriptures, ſence I was a iudge, more hedefully and attentely, then euer I dyd before,
<pb facs="tcp:8474:14"/> Therfore ye ſhall not nede to haue the matter deuolued vnto an other iudge. Now yf ye haue any thynge agaynſte this woman, ſpeake, and ye ſhal haue audience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Knouuleg.</speaker>
               <p>holde ye your opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſtyll that ye are ordeyned of all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty god, and I pray you in what place of the Bible dyd God order you maſtres miſſa?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphir.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt ordined the bleſſed meſſe in the .xxvi. of Math. the .xiiii: of Marke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxii. of Luke and in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xi. of the former epiſtel to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouulege.</speaker>
               <p>there is no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the meſſe in any of theſe places</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphiry.</speaker>
               <p>What maketh mater, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the name be ther or no, yf the thing be there. We ought rather to ſeke for the thynge it ſelfe alwayes more, then for the name of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouulege.</speaker>
               <p>How do men diſcerne and knowe thynges, but by theyr names? then ſeynge that ther is no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made of the meſſe, in theſe places reherſed, howe ſhall we knowe that Chriſte ordeyned the meſſe there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphiry.</speaker>
               <p>ye ſhall knowe, that Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8474:14"/> ordeyned the Meſſe by Chriſtes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, wherwyth he ordeyned that thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, that we call the meſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knowlege.</speaker>
               <p>Reherſe the wordes I pray you, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth Chriſte inſtitued the meſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyry.</speaker>
               <p>theſe they be: <hi>Dominus Ieſus in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a nocte, qua traditus eſt. etc.</hi> The Lorde Ieſus in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ntght, that he was betrayed toke breade and after that he had gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes he brake it and ſayd: Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, eate, thys is my bodye whyche is broken for you: doo this in the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of me. After the ſame maner, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ehe the cup, after the ſupper was don, and ſayd, This cup is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in my bloude, doo ye thys as oft as ye ſhall drynke, in the remembraunce of me. By theſe wordes, dyd Chriſte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtytute and ordeyne the Meſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege.</speaker>
               <p>And wyth the ſame wordes he inſtituted the Lordes ſuppe, then is the Meſſe and the Lordes ſupper all one thynge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphyry.</speaker>
               <p>They are all one thynge in verye dede, therfore, they that rayle agaynſte the bleſſed
<pb facs="tcp:8474:15"/> Meſſe, rayll alſo agaynſte the ſupper of our Lorde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Knouuleg.</speaker>
               <p>Yf the Meſſe and the ſupper of the Lorde be all one thyng, the ryghtes, the houſell, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Chriſtes body and bloud, and the ſupper of the Lorde are al one thynge: then the meſſe, the houſell, the rightes, the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloude, and the ſupper of the Lorde, ar all one thyng. Wherof it fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that whoſoeuer may celebrate or do any of theſe: may alſo celebrate or doo all the reſt: But all the lay men in Englande may celebrate the ſupper of the Lord, and may receiue theyr rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes or houſell, as well as preiſtes, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they may all celebrate or do meſſe as well as preiſtes may. Yf the ſupper of the Lord or houſtyng and the meſſe be all one thyng: whatſoeuer then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth vnto the one, belongethe alſo vnto the other: and what ſoeuer is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyred to the celebratynge of the one, is alſo requyred to the celebratyng of the other: But a ſhauen croune, a prei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es
<pb facs="tcp:8474:15"/> goun, an albe, a ſtole, a veſtiment, confiteor, miſereatur, collectes, ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſecretes, canon, memento, eleuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſacramente, remembraunce of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayntes departed, offering vp of chriſt for remiſſyon of ſynnes, breakynge of breade in .iii, partes: one for them that ar in Purgatory, an other for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are in heauen, the thyrde for them that are alyue, waſhynge of a mannes fyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, myxynge of water and wyne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther, ar neceſſarily requyred of him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat ſhall ſaye meſſe, then yf it be true that ye ſay, that the meſſe and Chriſtes ſupper, whych the common people cal, theyr houſell or ryghtes, are all one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hyng, then is it requyred, that all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whych ſhall celebrate the Lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or receyue theyr howſel, muſt haue ſhaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crounes, preſtes gownes, albes, ſtoles and veſtimentes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes: they muſt ſay ſecretes, and ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, collectes &amp; cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: they muſt breake the hooſte in .iii. partes, and offer vp of freaſhe, Chriſtes body for remiſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8474:16"/> of ſynne, wyth all the other ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons toyes and bables aboue reherſed: But theſe ar not requyred of hym that ſhal celebrate the ſupper of the Lorde, and yet are requyred of him that ſhall celebrate meſſe: it foloweth therfore that the ſupper of Chriſt and the meſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are not all one. More ouer yf the ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per of the Lorde and the meſſe were al one: when as a lay man maye as wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> receyue the ſupper of the Lorde for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> preiſt as a preiſt can do for a lay man then might a layman as wel ſay meſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for a preiſte, as a preiſt can do for a la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But I do not doubt, but ye think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that to be an inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenience, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to your ofte commended order, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it not conueniente, that the ſupper o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſte and the meſſe, ſhoulde be rek<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned all one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philargyrus.</speaker>
               <p>Me thynk that ye ſpake of late wonderous v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſcretly and vnreuerently, and othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wyſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it becommed a Chriſten ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to doo: where as ye called the holy v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtimentes whyche the preiſte weare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8474:16"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the honoure of Chriſte, who is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the meſſe, ſuperſtitious toyes and bables, ſeyng that they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to holy vſes by holy prayers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd by the inuocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of goddes name. When ye go to ſpeake with a great ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o ye not wel to put on the beſt clothes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat ye haue? ſhall a preiſte then doo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>miſſe when he putteth on better clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people wereth whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot only ſpeaketh w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, but alſo toucheth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he king of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye muſt not therfore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> raſhly diſpiſe the hallowed veſtime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es &amp; other ſuche lyke outward ſemely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eremonies, which ſerue for a good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouulege.</speaker>
               <p>I perceyue well, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s ye can not anſwerere to the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, whyche I haue made vnto youre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llowe, ye would drawe me craftelye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>te of the matter in to an other newe matter. But leaſte I ſhoulde ſeme to be vnable to anſwere vnto youre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, I ſaye, the veſtymentes for all the Byſſhoppes bablynge are no holyer, then Tom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tynkers taberd
<pb facs="tcp:8474:17"/> is, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of God is abuſed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is called vpon, to ſanctify thynges that God neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifyed or hallowed. Chriſtes naturall body is not now honoured w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> outward garmentes, and he wyl not be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red otherwiſe, then he hath commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: for he hath gyuen no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munte ſo to be honoured. And as for hys godhede, becauſe it is a ſpyrite, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſte be ſpyrytually worſhypped in ſprite and in truth, and not in outward veſtime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. Yf ye wyll worſhyp Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bodye, as ye oughte to doo, gyue good newe clothes vnto the naked or to the poore, that haue nede of clothes and then doo ye honour Chriſte as ye ſhoulde do. But to returne vnto oure purpoſe agayne, I axe of you, whether a lay man when he taketh hys rygtes at Eaſter in loue and charite wyth a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith, celebrateth the hole ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or no?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philargy.</speaker>
               <p>I graunt that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> celebrateth the hoſe ſupper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouulege</speaker>
               <p>but the ſame celebrateth not the hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:8474:17"/> and the ſupper of the Lorde are not all one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphiry.</speaker>
               <p>As a naked man now wythin this houre clothed, dyffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not in ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce from hym ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is clothed: ſo the meſſe, dyffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not from the ſupper of the Lorde, becauſe it hath decent apparell nowe, ſemely for ſuch a myſtery, whyche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce it had not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> primatiue church or elles there is no difference at al, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the Meſſe and the ſupper of our Lorde: for there is in the meſſe before the conſecration, breade and wyne, and after the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecration, the body &amp; bloud of Chriſt, and theſe are in the ſupper of our Lorde, and alſo in the meſſe, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the meſſe and the Supper of oure Lorde are al one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouulege.</speaker>
               <p>Ye ſay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is breade and wyne in the meſſe before the conſecration, and the body and bloude of Chriſt after the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, and theſe ar both in the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, and alſo in the meſſe, therfore, that the ſupper of the Lorde and the meſſe are all one. Fyrſt ye doo ſuppoſe to be
<pb facs="tcp:8474:18"/> true which is playn falſe, that is wher ſoeuer breaed and wyne is, &amp; the bodye and bloude of Chriſte is, that there is Chriſtes ſupper. At the maryage in the Cane of Galile, was breade and wyne, and the body and bloud of Chriſt more truly, then they are now in your meſſe: yet was not Chriſtes ſupper there. In the Supper alſo of the Corynthyans, which they eate before the Lordes ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, was breade and wyne, and (yf it be true, that the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taries hold, that Chriſtes body is in euery place,) there was Chriſtes body and bloude, but for all that, that ſupper was not Chriſtes ſupper, becauſe it was not done in the remembraunce of Chriſtes deathe, but onely to fyll the belly, and not to fede the ſoule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphiry.</speaker>
               <p>thys is not a lyke caſe, for neyther in the Cane of Galile, neyther in the Corynthyans Supper was, the wordes of conſecration ſayd and therfore was there no ſupper of oure Lorde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knowelege.</speaker>
               <p>Then yf the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>des of conſecration had bene ſayd
<pb facs="tcp:8474:18"/> in the Corynthyans ſupper, thoughe the Corynthyans hadde not intended to haue remembred Chryſtes deathe, theyr former ſupper ſhoulde haue bene chriſtes ſupper, and now by your reſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, when and where ſoeuer a preiſte ſayth the wordes of conſecratyon, as ye call them, ouer breade and wyne, there is Chryſtes ſupper, as thoughe in theſe it. thynges alone to haue breade wyne and certayne wordes ſayd ouer the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, ſhoulde conſyſte Chriſtes ſupper: whyche opynion I wyll take in hande to proue falſe by the autorite of goddes word. Luke in the .xxii. chap. deſcribing the Lordes ſupper &amp; al ſuch thinges as belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge vnto it, in theſe wordes: do this in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of me, teacheth vs plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one of the chefe pointes that belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes ſupper is to call to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of chriſt. And paul in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xi. chap. of the former epiſtle to the cori<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s writeth of chriſtes ſupꝑ thus Take ye eat ye this is my body which is broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for you: do this in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of
<pb facs="tcp:8474:19"/> me. After the ſame maner alſo, he toke the cuppe, when ſupper was done and ſayd: thys cup is the new teſtament in my bloude, do thys (as oft as ye ſhall drinke it) in the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of me, for as oft as ye ſhal eat of thys bread, and drynke of thys cup, ye ſhall declare the death of the lord vntyl he come. Theſe are the wordes of ſaynt Paule and the vndoubted ſcripture: wherevpon I gather, that it belongeth as muche to Chriſtes ſupper to receyue the breade and wyne in the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſt, and to declare and ſhew hys death, as it belongethe to reherſe theſe wordes, thys is my bodye, yea and more to: for ſainte Paule ſayeth, as oft as ye ſhall eate thys breade and drynke thys cup, ye ſhall declare and ſet furth the death of the Lord vntyll he come. He ſayeth not. as oft as ye ſhal eate thys breade and drynke thys cup, ye ſhall ſay theſe wordes ouer the breade and wyne, this is my bodye and thys is my bloude.</p>
               <p>Then doth not onely breade and wym
<pb facs="tcp:8474:19"/> and the wordes of conſecration ſayde by a preſt, make the ſupper of the lord, excepte the remembraunce of Chriſtes death, &amp; the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Chriſtes church be annexed alſo therunto. Then doo I gather this argument, the meſſe is not done in the remembraunce of Chriſte, as oft as it is done therfore: the meſſe is not the ſupper of the lord. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, that the meſſe and the ſupper of the Lorde, dyffer no more one from an other, then a naked man and a clothed man do: thys argumente ſhall ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently declare. Whoſe operationes and endes doo differ, and are dyuerſe, they are alſo dyuerſe thynges, and dyffer, and can not be all one: But the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and endes of Chriſtes ſupper and the meſſe are dyuerſe, and dyffer one from an other: therfore the ſupper of Chriſt and the meſſe do dyffer, and are diuerſe thinges, and can not be al one. The operation and ende of the Meſſe are theſe to purchaſſe remiſſion of ſyn by offerynge vp of Chriſte agayne to
<pb facs="tcp:8474:20"/> make fayre wether and rayne, to heale ſycke horſes, meſeld ſwyne, &amp; the french pox, to bryng ſoules to reſt that are in tormente and payne, to delyuer ſoules out of hel. The meſſe is ſayd and done in the remembraunce and honoure of men. Thys is alſo an operation at the meſſe, to purge ſynnes, and to take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> awaye, and to brynge the kyngdome of heauen, by the receyuyng of breade and wyne. The fyrſt ende or inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meſſe whereof I made mention, is declared in this ſecret. <hi>Satiſfaciat tibi domine etc.</hi> We beſeche thee Lord tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the offering vp of thys preſente ſacrifyce, maye be a ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſoule of thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. It is alſo declared in this prayer which is ſayde at the ende of euery meſſe. <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceat tibi ſancta Trinitas. etc.</hi> O holy Trinite, let thys obedyente ſeruyce of my ſeruytude pleaſe thee, that thys ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice which I vnworthy haue offered vnto the eyes of thy maieſty, maye be vnto thee acceptable, and thou hauing
<pb facs="tcp:8474:20"/> pytie, may be propiciable and purche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of mercy. The ſame intent is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in thys ſecrete whych is conteyned in the meſſe, whych is ſayde on the .xv. Sonday after Trinite ſondaye: <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede nobis domine queſumus, ut hec ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio ſalutaris, et noſtrorum fiat purgatio peccatorum, et tuae propitiatio pietatis.</hi> Lorde graunte vs we beſeche thee, that thys holſom oblation may be the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and clenſyng of our ſynnes. &amp;c. Alſo in the ſecrete of ſaynte Richarde, the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and ende of the meſſe is vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red playnly in theſe wordes. <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cede que ſumus miſericors deus. etc.</hi> Graunte vs mercyfull god, that by the interceſſyon of ſaynte Richarde thy confeſſor and Byſhoppe, thys rewarde offered to the eyes of thy maieſty, may both purchaſe vs grace to lyue well, and get vs euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting glori. Alſo that the purpoſe and inter of the meſſe is to ſaue both y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body &amp; the ſoule: The ſecret in S. Romanes meſſe doth euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly teſtifi in theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: <hi>Sacrifitiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie.</hi> we beſech y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8474:21"/> almyghty god, loke mekeky to, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde the ſacrifice of our deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and of thy benygnite at the interceſſyon of thy confeſſor &amp; byſhop Romane grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thorow thys, health of bothe body and ſoule. Now by theſe wordes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meſſe here reherſed, it is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that the ende and intent of the meſſe is to make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes ſoule, to purches mercy, to purge ſynne awaye by offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge vp of ſacryfyce, and to obtayne euerlaſtyng glory. Hath the ſupper of the Lorde I pray you any ſuch opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, intent, purpoſe and ende, as theſe be? Neuer one Another ende and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the meſſe, is to make fayre we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; rayne. Theſe titles in the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal: <hi>Miſſa pro ſerenitate aeris. Miſſa pro pluuia,</hi> doo ſufficiently teſtify. Thys doth alſo teſtify the ſecret of the meſſe ſayde for rayne. <hi>O blat is domine placare muneribus. etc.</hi> Lorde, be thou ſwaged by the rewardes offered vp: and gyue vs the helpe of ſufficient rayne in dew ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Hath the lordes ſupper any ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:8474:21"/> operation or intente? That an other operation and ende of the Meſſe is to heale ſycke horſes, meſeled ſwyne, and al other diſeaſes, both of men and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, theſe titles beare ſufficiently wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: <hi>Miſſa ꝓ peſte an imaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> A meſſe for the morte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or peſtiferoꝰ ſykneſſes of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes. <hi>Miſſa Raphaelis archa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geli pro om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus infirmit atibus,</hi> A meſſe or Rapha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ell the archangel, for all ſyckneſſes. Is Chriſtes ſupper co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued for any ſuche purpoſe? that the meſſe is alſo ſayd to delyuer ſoules out of payne and torment, the meſſe of, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiem,</hi> in theſe wordes beareth recorde <hi>Pro quorum memoria. etc.</hi> Lorde, gyue them euerlaſtynge reſt, for whoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, the body of Chriſte is receyued. And in this, <hi>Poſt communionem,</hi> after theyr communion. <hi>Annue nobis do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine per hoc ſacrificium quod ſumpſimꝰ etc.</hi> graunt vs Lord by thys ſacrifice, whych we haue receyued y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſoules of thy ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes may deſerue to rece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> forgiuenes of theyr ſynnes. Wher did
<pb facs="tcp:8474:22"/> Chriſte ordene that his ſupper ſhoulde be taken to delyuer ſoules oute of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente? That an other operation and ende of the meſſe is to delyuer ſoules out of hell, thys place red in the meſſe of, <hi>Requiem.</hi> doth beaer ſufficient wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. <hi>Hoſtias &amp; preces tibi domine offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimus. etc.</hi> Lorde we offer vp vnto the oblatyons and prayers, receyue thou them Lorde, for thoſe ſoules, whom we remembre thys daye, make them Lord to paſſeouer from deathe to lyfe. And in thys prayer: <hi>Domine Ieſu Chriſte rex gloriae. etc.</hi> is playne mention mayde of delyueraunce from hell, wythoute any figure or trope. Lord Ieſu Chriſt king of glory delyuer the ſoules of al fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full dede men frome the hande of Hell and from the depe lake. And in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer of Gregories Trentalle thys is the ende of the Meſſe to delyuer ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les oute of the handes of deuelles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iuſtorum animae in man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dei ſunt nec noc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>t eis tormentum malitiae.</hi> The
<pb facs="tcp:8474:22"/> ryghteouſe mennes ſoules are in God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des handes neyther ſhall any tormente of malyce vex them. Then it dothe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, that the Meſſe goeth aboute to delyuer euell and dampned mennes ſoules from the place, where they are, that is, from Hell and from the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the deuell. Where tormentethe any Deuell any ſoules departed, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge onely in hell? therfore the intent of the Meſſe is to delyuer foules oute of hall. The wordes of the Trentall meſſe are theſe. <hi>Deus ſumma ſpes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae redemptionis qui in terra promiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis. et cetera.</hi> God the chefe hope of pure redemptyon whyche haſte choſen before all other landes to be borne in the lande of Promyſe, and ſufferedeſt death in the ſame place: Delyuer mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfully the Soule of thy ſeruaunte, frome the handes of Deuelles. Loo, here maye ye ſe, that the operation of the Meſſe, is too delyuer Soules frome the handes of Deuylles. Dyd Chryſte ordeyne hys Supper to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer
<pb facs="tcp:8474:23"/> ſoules from the handes of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelles? ſuerly theyr is no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made of any ſuch mater in the inſtitution of Chriſtes ſupper. That the meſſe is a memorial of ded me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is done in the honoure of ſayntes, the wordes of the meſſe, hereafter folowyng, do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtlye declare. <hi>Pro quorum memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria corpus Chriſti ſumitur. etc.</hi> Lord gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue them euerlaſtynge reſt, in whoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce the body of Chriſt is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued. This is ſayd in an other meſſe <hi>Aſſume queſumus omnipotens deus in honore. etc.</hi> We beſeche the Lorde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty, take thes oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s offered vp vnto thee, in the honour of ſaynt Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtach, and hys fellowes. And it is ſayd in an other meſſe. <hi>Hoſtias tibi domine pro commemoratione ſancti Lamberti.</hi> Lorde, we offer vp vnto thee, oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s for the remembraunce of ſaynt La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bert thy martyr and biſhop. Was Chriſtes ſupper ordeyned for the remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce only of chriſtes paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? Or is was alſo ordeyned for the remembraunce of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:8474:23"/> whych at but his ſeruauntes? That ye meſſe intendeth to take ſynnes awaye by the offerynge of breade and wyne vnconſecrated, this ſecrete with an. C. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>no doth teſtify. <hi>Feria quarta poſt letare Supplices te rogamus omnipotens deus ut his ſacrificiis peccata noſtra munden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quia tunc. etc.</hi> Almyghtye God we humbly beſeche thee, that oure ſynnes maye be clenſed by theſe ſacrifices: for then thou gyueſte the true health both of body and ſoule. Theſe wordes ſayth the preiſt before the ſacring onely, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge vnconſecrated wyne in the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyce, and vnconſecrated breade liynge vpon the chalice. Now haue I proued by the very wordes of the meſſe, that the ende of the meſſe is to purchaſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, by offeryng of breade &amp; wyne, to deſerue euerlaſtynge lyfe by recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge and offeryng of Chriſtes body, to make fayre wether &amp; rayne to heale all ſyckneſſes to bringe ſoules fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hel, and to delyuer them from tormentes, to honour ſayntes, and to make a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall
<pb facs="tcp:8474:24"/> of ſayntes deathes, and nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites, of the receyuyng of Chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloud, and otherwhyles to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke the ſame of the offerynge of breade and wyne. Theſe are the operations, intentes, and endes of the meſſe, and the ſame are not the endes and operations of the ſupper of the Lorde, for the ende of chriſtis ſupper is to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber chriſtes death, to gyue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes for our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre, that we all are me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of one body, and ought therfore one to loue an other. Therfor the endes of the meſſe &amp; the operations of the ſame, and the ende and intent of Chriſtes ſupper are diuerſe, and differ much one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>other: whereupon it foloweth, that the meſſe and Chryſtes ſupper doo dyffer, and ar not al one. Then can ye not ſay, that the meſſe was ordeyned of God, in the xxvi. of Mathew and that the meſſe is the ſupper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde decked &amp; ſemely appoynted with dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t apparell for ſuch a miſtery.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Palemon.</speaker>
               <p>Yf ye haue no other places of ſcrypture, to proue hat the
<pb facs="tcp:8474:24"/> meſſe was ordeyned of god, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye haue hyther to brought, furthe ſhe muſte be dryue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of Chriſtes church, as a mere inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfor yf ye haue any mo places, bryng them furth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philargy.</speaker>
               <p>The meſſe is good, &amp; all goodnes is of god, as S. Iames ſayeth: euery good gyft, and euery perfect gyft is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, deſcendynge from the father of lyght: ergo the meſſe is of god. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer Chriſt ſayeth in the .xiiii. of Iohn That co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forter, which is the holy ghoſt, whom the father ſhal ſend in my name, he ſhall teach you all thinges what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer I ſhall ſpeake vnto you. Loo, here Chriſte promyſeth that the holy Ghoſt ſhal teach the Apoſtles and the church all thynges, that he ſhall ſpeake af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hys Aſcenſion. Then dyd Chriſte doubtles tell the Churche many thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges after hys Aſcenſyon, whyche the holy Ghoſte taught a greate whyle af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and emonge thoſe thynges, that were onely taught after the aſcention, was the meſſe. Alſo Iohn. xvi. Chap:
<pb facs="tcp:8474:25"/> Chriſte ſayeth, I haue many thynges to ſay vnto you, whych ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not beare now, but when he ſhall come whych is the ſpirite of truthe, he ſhall lede you into all truth: Beholde here, how that Chriſte dyfferred to ſhew the Apoſtles certayne verites, tyll that he was aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp into heauen. They was there ſome truthes tolde to the churche after that Chriſte was aſcended, which was not tolde of Chriſte, before hys aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion: of and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is no mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made in the .iiii. Euangeliſtes. And ſurely, as I haue ſayde, the meſſe is one of them whyche was not iaught before the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention, but aftet it, as our mother the holy churche beleueth, whoſe doctrine I wyll rather folowe then all the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans in Germany, though therwer CCCCC. tymes as many mo, then now are. <hi>Magis enim credendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt Marie veraci<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> iudeorum turbae fallaci.</hi> Saye not nowe but that ye haue now ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alleged you, to proue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the meſſe is of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Knouuleg.</speaker>
               <p>Ye make a reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb facs="tcp:8474:25"/> and brynge furthe ſcripture, to proue that the Meſſe is of God: But howe ſtrong your reaſon is, and how rightly ye haue alleged the ſcrypture, I ſhall ſhortly declare. Where as ye reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the meſſe is good, &amp; al goodnes is of God, ergo the meſſe is of God: ye commyt a fallacy or a deceytful dryft of ſophiſtry whych is called of the Logicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which hate ſuch ſophiſticall deceytes, <hi>Petitio principii,</hi> that is when a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyl proue a thynge to be true, by the ſame thinge, or wyth an other, that is as doubtfull as that is, which is called into queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The chefe matter that we go aboute in thys accuſation, is too proue that the meſſe is vngodly &amp; full of blaſphemy, and therfore ought to be put out of the church. And yet ye very wyttely allege thys for a prynciple, and out of al con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſy, that the meſſe is good, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that therfore it is of God. No no ſyr, ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not bleare my eyes ſo. Proue ye fyrſt that the meſſe is good and then ſhal I graunt you your concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that
<pb facs="tcp:8474:26"/> it is of God. To the place whych ye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege out of the .xiiii. of Iohn: wherwith ye would proue that Chriſt taught the Apoſtles &amp; the church certayn doctrine that he taught not before his aſcentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherof ye ſaye that the meſſe is one: I anſwere, that ye allege the ſcrypture falſe: for it is not in the text as yon al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege it, he ſhall teache you what ſoeuer I ſhall ſaye vnto you, but what ſoeuer I haue ſaid vnto you. I take to witnes both Eraſmus tranſlation &amp; the Greke text which is thus. <hi>Ekinosymas didaxi panta kai ypomneſi ymas panta oſa eipon ymin:</hi> that is to ſay, he ſhall teache you all thynges &amp; put you in remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of al thynges whatſoeuer I haue ſayd vnto you. And here may all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſe, how crafte ye and vnfaythfully ye cite the ſcrypture, allegynge one tence for an other, and leauynge out the pryncipall part of the ſentence. As touchynge the place whiche ye allege oute of the .xvi. of Iohn: in theſe wordes: I haue many hinges to, ſay vnto you, but ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not
<pb facs="tcp:8474:26"/> beare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhall come which is the ſpriet of truth, he ſhal lede you into all truth. I anſwer, that ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not proue by this place, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the holy goſt taught the church any doctrine, which the Apoſtles &amp; Euangeliſtes haue not left behinde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> en theyr wrytinges. Yf ye ſay that they could not abide diuers thinges before Chriſtes aſcentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I ſay that they could abyde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame after hys aſcentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yf ye would apply in this ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce this (word) you, only vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles tyme, &amp; not to the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, ye do the apoſtles playn wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, for Chriſt ſayd theſe wordes vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what can ye gather of this place? Chriſt promiſed the apoſtles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the holy ghoſt ſhould lead the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into all truth, dyd he ſo or no? yf he performed his promiſe, the knew the apoſtles all truth &amp; no parte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth was vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The apoſtles alſo was eyther vnfaithfull &amp; diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes vnto chriſt, or thei were faithfull &amp; obedient. Yf they were faithful &amp; obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, thei kept thes his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes
<pb facs="tcp:8474:27"/> Speake that in the lyghte, whyche I ſpake in darkenes, and ſpeake ye that openly, that ye haue hearde pryuely. But Chriſte taught by the holy ghoſt the Apoſtles, all truthe, then were they eyther diſobedient ſeruauntes or elles they taughte in theyr wryttynges all truth. Yf they taught al truth in theyr wryttinges, &amp; yet taught not the meſſe ther in, it foloweth that it is no partt of the trueth, &amp; ſo not of god. Becauſe that ye thynke, that Chriſt taught the churche ſome holſome doctrine, that he taught not the Apoſtles: I praye you whether ſhewed god the father, his ſon Chriſt, al truth and all doctrine neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for a Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man to knowe or no? yf he dyd: then the Apoſtles learned of Chriſte all truthe, and euery neceſſary doctrine for a chriſten man, For Chriſt ſayeth Iohn. xv. I haue ſhewed you al thynges whyche I haue hearde of my father. Yf that Chriſt hath not taught them al thynges neceſſary for a Chriſti man to know, then were they vnperfit
<pb facs="tcp:8474:27"/> Chriſten men, and in an euell caſe: Yf Chriſt haue taught the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all truthe, and they woulde not teache vs that agayn in theyr Epiſtles and Goſples, they were both vnkind vnto vs, &amp; diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent perſones to Chriſt, whych co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them to teache vs all ſuch thinges as he taught the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before: but they were both kynde vnto vs, and obedient vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theyr mayſter Chriſte: Therefore, they taughte in theyr wryttynges, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, in the Epiſtles and Goſpels, al hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom doctrine and neceſſary, for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten man to know. Therfore the .ii. pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which ye haue alleged out of Iohn make nothyng for the meſſe, and ſuche other vnwrytten vanytes, but declare the weakenes and imperfytnes of the Apoſtles whych wyth out the helpe of the holy ghoſt, could neyther reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre, nor vnderſtande, after Chriſtes reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, ſuch thinges as he had taught them before his paſſion. But for a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tryall of the matter, put the caſe that chriſt had taught the church after
<pb facs="tcp:8474:28"/> the apoſtles deathes, certayn holſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, whyche he had not taught the apoſtles in theyr tyme: (which thynge no chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyl graunt) yet it folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the meſſe ſhould be that hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſom &amp; neceſſary doctrine, for it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vnto the nature of God, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth no vnconſtancy, to teach a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary doctrine, after his aſcenſion vnto that, which he taught before his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But the meſſe is clene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary vnto the doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine, which he taught before his paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſpecially vnto thys. <hi>Nemo uenit ad patrem niſi per me.</hi> Noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> commeth vnto the father but throw me, therfore Chriſt neuer taught the meſſe, neyther before his aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor after. And where as ye allege, that the church beleueth, that the holy ghoſt reueled vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy fathers, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meſſe after the apoſtles time, what churche meane ye of: the Popes churche, or of Chriſtes true church? Yf ye meane of the Popes church we, wote howe muche credence oughte to be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto the Popes lemman. Yf ye
<pb facs="tcp:8474:28"/> meane of Chriſtes true churche, when ye: ſaye that the true churche of Chriſte beleueth, that the holy ghoſte reueled the meſſe vnto the fathers, and not to the Apoſtles, eyther ye take violently away the Apoſtles from Chriſtes true churche, or elles lye ſhamfully, in ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge that Chriſtes churche beleueth a thynge, when as the pryncipall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres of Chriſtes churche neyther doo, nor dyd at any time beleue it. Now ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue I ſufficiently proued, that al that ye could hytherto bryng furth, could not proue that the meſſe had any fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>datio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ground of goddes word. Nowe my lord iudge, I reporte me vnto you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the places, which this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſed, be ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, or no, to proue that the meſſe is of god.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Palemon.</speaker>
               <p>your pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces alleged out of Iohn, make as much for the meſſe as thei do for the popes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premecy, pilgrimage, pardons, purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, &amp; any other ſuch thing, wherof is no mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made in holy ſcriptur. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ye muſt ether bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g furth ſomeother ſcripture, for your purpoſe, or els grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:8474:29"/> that the meſſe is not of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphiry.</speaker>
               <p>We are not ſo ſklenderly prouided but that we haue yet both ſcripture, &amp; alſo reaſon, wherewyth we ſhall be able to proue, that the meſſe is of God. Fyrſte vnto you maſters, whyche accuſe the meſſe, I axe of you, whether almyghty God requyreth in thys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, honor thy father and mother, as well obedience of ſubiectes, vnto magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and ruelers, as he requyreth obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of chyldren, to theyr fathers and mothers?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knoweleg.</speaker>
               <p>yes al a lyke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyry.</speaker>
               <p>Then ar ſubiectes as wel bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to obey the rulers commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, as chyldren are bounde too obey theyr fathers and mothers commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouueleg.</speaker>
               <p>That do I graunt alſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphyry.</speaker>
               <p>But the rulers haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all vs, that be theyr ſubiectes, to beleue that the Meſſe is of God, and therfore to come vnto it: therfore all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are bounde in payne of dampnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to beleue that the meſſe is goddes ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, and to come to it. But leaſt ye
<pb facs="tcp:8474:29"/> ſhoulde doubte, that any magiſtrate hath commaunded the meſſe to be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the ordinaunce of God, ye haue ſene the daye youre ſelfe, wyth in theſe .viii. yeres, that he that woulde haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agaynſt the bleſſed meſſe, ſhould haue ben burned, as a traytor to god, bafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon to the kyng: whych they would not haue done, yf that they would not haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had the meſſe to be taken, for the very ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God. And I am ſure, that there are in Englande, many inferior magiſtrates, whyche are of that ſame mynde ſtyll, and commaunde at thys houre their inferiours, to come to meſſe and commaunde them to beleue that it is of God. How many Biſhoppes and iuſtices of Peace are ther now in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, whyche are not ſuche, as I haue reherſed? Therfore yf we be bounde to obey our polytike fathers, we muſte be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leue that the meſſe is of god.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouulege</speaker>
               <p>Wythin theſe .xx. yeres there haue ben ſome magiſtrates, whyche haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded theyr ſubyectes in peyne of
<pb facs="tcp:8474:30"/> death to beleue that the biſhop of rome, was heede of the churche. Is not thys the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t euen now of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour &amp; alſo of the Frenche kynge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde not theſe .ii. magiſtrates in payne of burning, all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beleue, that pilgrimag is good, worſhyppi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges is an godly, mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kery is holy kinde of lyfe? Now I pray you, ar al theſe .ii. magiſtrates ſubiectes bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in payne of dampnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the biſhop of Rome is heed of the churche? are they bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to beleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pilgrimage &amp; worſhp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ping of images ar good &amp; gudli? ar thei bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to beleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kery is a kinde of lyfe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſeth god: are theſe ſubiectes bound to beleue any more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crede, &amp; in the expreſſed word of god? anſwer I pray you, ar al the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours ſubiectes, &amp; the Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che kinges ſubiectes bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to beleue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the pope is the heed of the church, &amp; that pardones pilgrimage, &amp; mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kery be of god?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
               <p>They ar not bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the pope is hed of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, neither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pilgrimag
<pb facs="tcp:8474:30"/> is of god.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kno.</speaker>
               <p>The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ar not al ſubiectes, by the vertue of the fyrſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to beleue, what ſoeuer the rulers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beleue except it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde, be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyned in the expreſſed word of god: But ther is no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in the ſcripture of the meſſe, therfore though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magiſtrate ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beleue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the meſſe were of god, yet they ar not bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to obey the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that caſe. Thus much haue we gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of you by your awn confeſſion. Now let vs ſe what we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyn of you by the ſcriptur. We grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we muſt obey the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the politike father, ſo far as he kepeth him ſelfe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in his bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, in all thinges, that are for the glory of God, or are profitable for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welthe, and not contrary vnto the worde of God. But yf he woulde goo beyonde hys boundes, that is, yf he woulde commaunde men to beleue, that thynge to be a worſhyppynge of god, whych is eyther vnſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of in the written worde of god, or contrary vnto
<pb facs="tcp:8474:31"/> he ſame worde, or yf he ſhoulde forbyd thys worde, or any parte of it, we are not bounde to obeye hym in thys caſe. My auctoris ſaynt Paule, whyche, in the Epiſtle to the Galathians, ſayeth, Yf that I, or an angell of heauen doo ſhew any Goſpel beſyde it, that I haue ſhewed you, accurſed be he, &amp; excu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God. And the ſame he ſayeth vnto the Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: that that I haue receyued of the Lorde, that I haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vnto you. And in the Epiſtle to the Galathia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, he ſayeth, that he recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Goſpel which he had preached, not of any man, but by the reuelation of Ieſus Chriſte. Then the meanynge of ſaynt Paule is, that he woulde that euen hys awn ſelfe, or an Angel of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſhould be accurſed, yf eyther of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould teache or commaunde to beleue any doctrine, that he hath not receyued of Chriſt: wherof I gather, that al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, whyche commaunde to be taught &amp; beleued any doctrine of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tydynges, whych they haue not recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:8474:31"/> of Chriſte, that they ar accurſed by the doctrine of ſaynte Paule. Daniell obeyed hys kynge, ſo longe as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded hym, not to doo any thynge, agaynſt Goddes commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: but when hys maſter would haue had him to haue worſhipped Bel &amp; the drago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he woulde not obeye hym. The .iii. Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites obeyed kyng Nabuchodonoſor in al thinges, that perteyned vnto a king to requyre: but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the kyng went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde hys boundes, and woulde haue had the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue worſhypped hys yma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, they woulde no longer obeye theyr polytike father. The Aopſtles alſo in ciuile matters, obeyd the magiſtrates, and payde tribute, but when the rulers forbad the apoſtles to preach any more in Chriſtes name, they would not obey thyr commaundement: but ſayde. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius eſt obedire deo ꝙ hominibus:</hi> It is better to obey God, then men. By theſe places ye may ſe playnly, that we ar not bound to obey the magiſtrates, yf they commaunde vs to beleue any thynge,
<pb facs="tcp:8474:32"/> or do any thyng, that is contrary vnto ſcripture: but the Meſſe is contrarye vnto the ſcriptur, therfore, though the magiſtrate ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vs to bele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it were of god, we ar not bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to in this caſe obey the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Howbeit, in other caſes we ar bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to obey the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in payne of dampnation: for he that reſiſteth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any ſuch matters, as they haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorite of commaundement ouer, reſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth god and ſo purchaſſeth hym ſelfe the wrath of god.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphi.</speaker>
               <p>He that is not agaynſt me, is wyth me, ſayeth Chriſt: but the meſſe, for al your ſaiynge, is not agaynſt Chriſt and hys worde, ergo it is with Chriſt, and of chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knoweleg.</speaker>
               <p>That the meſſe is contrary to Chryſte and his holy worde, I ſhall be able too proue it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wytneſſes enough brought out of the ſcripture, and the Meſſe it ſelfe alſo. Thys is ſayde in the Meſſe, for auoydyng of the Peſtylence in the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe wordes in a prayer, called a ſecrete. <hi>Subueniat nobis domine. etc.</hi> Lorde, we beſeche thee, that the workynge of thys
<pb facs="tcp:8474:32"/> preſent ſacrifice, may helpe vs, whyche alſo may myghtely delyuer vs from al erroures, and ſaue vs from runnynge into all perditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Lo, here the working of a ſacrifice offered vp by a preiſte, is rekened and taken to haue as muche poure, as Chriſt hath, to helpe vs by his ſacrifice: for Chriſte wyth his ſacrifyce dyd no more but delyuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, &amp; ſaued vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all perdition or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruition. Now I pray you, how doth thys agre with Paul, that an other ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice then Chriſt offered, ſhold ſaue vs whyche ſayethe. Hebre .x. Wyth one oblatyon he hathe made perfyte for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore, all them, whyche are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed. Thys is ſayde in the Canon of the Meſſe. <hi>Hec ſacro ſancta commixtio corporis et ſanguinis domini. etc.</hi> Let thys mynglynge togyther of the body and bloude of oure Lorde Ieſu Chriſt be vnto me and to all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that receyue it, ſaluation of bothe bodye and ſoule to deſerue euerlaſting lyfe, &amp; a prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to helth to receiue it Behold as the
<pb facs="tcp:8474:33"/> meſſe teacheth men to beleue that they may purchaſe euerlaſtynge lyfe by the worke, bothe ordeyned and done by a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is, by the mynglyng together of the conſecrated breade and wyne in the chalyce. Where dyd God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de any preiſt or miniſter to mingle the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated breade and wyne togyther? in no place of the wrytten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orde of God. Is it not contrary vnto the ſcripture I reporte me to you, that the worke of a ſynfull man, ſhall deſerue euerlaſtyng lyfe? I ſuppoſe (ſayth ſaynt Paul) Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano .iii. that a man is Iuſtyfyed by fayth, wythout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes of the law: yf that a man be not iuſtified by the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, commaunded euen expreſſedly in Goddes law, ſhall a man be iuſtifyed and ſaued by a worke, neuer ones com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by god but inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtitious man? Se nowe, howe prately the ſcripture &amp; the meſſe do agre. The meſſe hath an other Prayer lyke vnto thys former, whyche begynneth thus. <hi>Domine ſancte pater omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s deus. etc.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8474:33"/> Holy Lorde almyghty father euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng God, graunt me, that I maye ſo worthely receyue the body and bloude of thy ſon our lord Ieſu Chriſt, that I maye deſerue therby to receyue forgy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenes of al my ſinnes, &amp; to be fylled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy holy ſprite and to haue thy peace. Marke here, how that it which is only giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> throw the merit of chriſtes paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and is only wrought by Chriſt, is cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued blaſphemouſly of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke wroght and done of a ſynful man. Is ther not here a ſwete agreyng wyth this prayer of the meſſe, &amp; theſe textes of ſcripture? <hi>Domini eſt ſalus. Nec eſt in alio quoꝙ ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus:</hi> Saluation is the Lordes, neyther is there ſaluation in any other. When ye haue done al thynges whych ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded you, ſay that ye were vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ſeruauntes. The meſſe in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary vnto the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, teacheth vs, that the offerynge vp of bread &amp; wyne, may do the ſame, that Chriſte dyd on the croſſe, that is, maye take away all our ſynnes &amp; may bryng
<pb facs="tcp:8474:34"/> helth to the lyuinge, and reſt to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphiry.</speaker>
               <p>Your talke dothe te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify, that ye are a Sacramentary, and that ye do not beleue, that after the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecration, the breade and wyne are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the fleſhe and bloud of Chriſt. When as the breade and wyne ar tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in to Chriſtes fleſhe and bloude, and of theſe two commethe furthe hole Chriſte, what ſynne is it, to craue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyuenes of ſynnes by the offerynge vp of our ſauioure Chriſte, whyche neuer ceſſethe frome takynge of the ſynnes of the worlde awaye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>
                  <hi>kno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uueleg.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>But what yf a man craue and axe the ſame thynge of the Offerynge vp of dreade and wyne, two poore creatures, as yet vnconſecrated.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphyry.</speaker>
               <p>He ſhoulde make a God of breade and wyne and ſo commytte Idolatry: For that is to euery man a god, of whom he loketh to haue ſaluation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouuelege.</speaker>
               <p>than is the meſſe an idolatreſſe, for ſhe axeth the benefit of ſa uation, of the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferynge vp bare breade &amp; wyne vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:8474:34"/>
               <speaker>Porphiry.</speaker>
               <p>how can ye proue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this that the meſſe axeth ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the offerynge of breade and wyne vnconſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crated and not of Chriſte?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knonuelege.</speaker>
               <p>I praye you in what place of the meſſe is the breade &amp; wyne turned into Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes body &amp; blou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphiry.</speaker>
               <p>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe wordes ar ſpoken ouer the bread and wyne, thys is my body, and this is the cup of my bloud &amp; of the new and euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſtyng teſtament.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouelge.</speaker>
               <p>And is the bread, bread ſtyll, &amp; the wyne, wyne ſtyl tyll thes wordes be ſaid ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread &amp; the wine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Por.</speaker>
               <p>ye verely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouu.</speaker>
               <p>But the wordes which I ſhall reherſe, are ſayd ſtreight way after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crede, a great while before the wordes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be ſaid &amp; the ordinary rubrik giueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſtes this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement, before they ſay the wordes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſpake of. Let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preiſt take the chalice in hys ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, &amp; ſet dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly in a dew vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the middes of the altare, and douke a lytle down, &amp; lyfte vp the chalice w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> both his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, offering the
<pb facs="tcp:8474:35"/> ſacrifice vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde, ſaiyng this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer: Receyue holy trinite this offering, whiche I an vnworthy ſynner offer in the honour of the, of the bleſſed virgyn Mary, &amp; of all ſayntes, for my ſynnes and offences, for the helth of the lyuing and for the reſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ar departed. This prayer is ſayd in euery meſſe, but now wyl I bring you diuerſe ſecretes, peculiar &amp; proper vnto diuerſe meſſes, of lyke wickednes &amp; impiete, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> it that I reherſed here before. This prayer is ſayde in the meſſe of ſayyte Griſgony. Lord, we beſech the, receyue our rewar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des wyth a pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenaunce, that by the interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy martyr bleſſed Griſgoni, they maye purge awaye all contagius infections of oure ſynnes. Thys is ſayde in the Meſſe of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſaint Steue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Lord, loke plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauntly vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſacrifice offered with the vowes of thy faithful, that it, which hath brought vnto thy beloued martyr Steuen &amp; his companions this dayes glory of theyr inuention, may profit vs
<pb facs="tcp:8474:35"/> to rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption &amp; grace. This is ſayde in the meſſe of Marke and Marcelliane. Lord, we beſech the, that thy grace may go before vs, &amp; alſo come after, &amp; take gentilly theſe oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which we offer vp for our ſinnes, to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated vnto thy name, that by the interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy martyres Marke &amp; Marcelliane, they may be profytable to ſaluation for all men. This is ſayde in the meſſe of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chomed is: Lord make holy the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices &amp; by the interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy bleſſed martyr Nichomedis, cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe &amp; purge vs by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, from the ſpottes of our ſynnes. This is red in the meſſe of S. Richrad Graunt vs mercyful god by the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of ſaint Richarde thy confeſſor and biſhop, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the rewarde offered vnto the eyes of thy maieſty, may get grace to lyue well, &amp; purchaſſe euerlaſtynge glory. The ſacrifices, oblations, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, which ar ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of here in theſe prayers, ar nothing els but bare bread &amp; bare wyne: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayers wherin thei ar offered, are ſayd longe before the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crynge
<pb facs="tcp:8474:36"/> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But the preiſte at meſſe axeth of god, that the offering vp of the ſame bare bread &amp; wine may take awaye ſynnes, purge the contagins in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fection of ſynnes awaye, may profit to our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption &amp; to obtayne grace, may be profitable to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may purge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpottes of ſynnes, &amp; may get grace and purches euerlaſtinge glory. Euery man beleueth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may obteyne that thing which he erneſtly doth aſke &amp; craue, but the meſſe or the preſt at meſſe axeth erneſtly purgation &amp; clenſyng of ſynnes, &amp; euerlaſtyng glory, to be gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god by the offering vp of bread and wyne: ergo the meſſe beleueth, that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes maye be purged and euerlaſtynge glory may be obteyned by the offering vp of bread &amp; wyne. But bread &amp; wyne ar not god, neyther is the offeryng vp of bread &amp; wyne any ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god but only the ordinaunce of man: Then they that beleue to be ſaued &amp; purged fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne by bread &amp; wyne, or by the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feryng vp of bread &amp; wyne, thinke that
<pb facs="tcp:8474:36"/> they may be ſaued by a thynge that is not God, and by a worke, that god ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. But as ye ſayd of late, that is to euery man his god, by whom he loketh to be ſaued and redemed from ſynne: but the meſſe wyth her chaplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes truſt to be ſaued by the offerynge vp of breade &amp; wyne, therfore the meſſe with her chaplaynes maketh a god of the offerynge vp of bread &amp; wyne. But all they that doo ſo, are Idolaters: but the meſſe and her chaplaynes doo ſo, ergo they are Idolaters. Now ſeynge that the meſſe is an Idolatres, what Chriſten man wyl from hence take her for Goddes ſeruice? Who darre for the diſpleaſure of God, come vnto her, or haue any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphy.</speaker>
               <p>it is not ſuch an hainus mater, as ye make it, to offer vp bread &amp; wyne Dyd not the preiſtes of Moyſes lawe, offer vp breade &amp; wyne? Dyd not alſo Melchiſedech a preiſte before Moyſes law, of whoſe order we ar of offer vp al ſo bred &amp; wine? &amp; yet wer nether Moſes
<pb facs="tcp:8474:37"/> Idolaters, nor yet Melchiſedech.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weleg.</speaker>
               <p>yf that the Preiſtes of Moyſes lawe and Melchiſedech had, wythout any commaundemente of God, offered vp breade and wyne, truſtynge by the offerynge therof, to purchaſſe redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cign and ſaluation, they had bene Ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laters in dede. But they neyther offred vp bread and wyne wythout commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente, neyther truſted they to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued thorowe the offerynge vp of bread and wyne: therfore theyr examples wyl not excuſe you from Idolatry. Where as ye ſaye, that ye are Preiſtes of the order of Melchiſedech, and ſeme therby to haue auctorite to offer vp bread and wyne, as he dyd I ſhall brefely proue, that ye are not of hys order. Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is a Preiſte of the order of Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech, is a preiſte for euer and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath begynnynge nor endynge of hys preſthode: and therfore was Chriſt called a Preiſt after the order of Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech, becauſe he was an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge preiſte, and hys preiſthode had
<pb facs="tcp:8474:37"/> effecte and ſtreyngth from the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the worlde, and ſhall haue vnto the ende of the worlde, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he offered breade and wyne, for he offered vp neyther of bothe, but his body and bloude, whyche was ſygny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the bread and the wyne: ye haue a begynnynge of youre preiſthode, at xxiiii. yeares of your age, and an ende of it when ye dye, therfore ye are not Preiſtes of the order of Melchiſedech. Are ye preiſtes of Moyſes lawe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largy.</speaker>
               <p>no.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouule.</speaker>
               <p>Yf that ye be neyther preiſtes of the order of Melchiſedech, neyther of Aarons order, by what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorite take ye in hande, to ſtande at al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tares, offerynge vp of outwarde ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, when as in the new Teſtamente, it is neyther laufull to bylde altare, neyther to offer vpon it any outwarde ſacrfeice, ſeynge, that by the ſacryfyce, that Chriſte offered on the croſſe, all altares and outwarde ſacryfyces were abrogated, and laufully put downe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphyry.</speaker>
               <p>We haue altares in the new
<pb facs="tcp:8474:38"/> te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamente, and outwarde Sacrifyces allowed alſo, euen of Chriſte in the .v. of Matthew in theſe wordes: When thou ſhalte offer vp thy rewarde at the altare, and ſhall there remembre that thy brother hath ſomethynge agaynſt thee, leaue thy rewarde ther before the altare, and go and be fyrſte broughte in fauoure wyth thy brother, and then come and offer thy rewarde. Lo, here oure maſter Chriſte maketh mention bothe of a rewarde and alſo of an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare. Therfore in the newe Teſtament we maye bothe haue altares, and alſo outwarde offerynges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouuelege.</speaker>
               <p>All they that haue any ryghte vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng in ſcriptur ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tel that Chriſt ſayd theſe wordes, whyche ye haue reherſed, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ieues: which as yet, wer vnder the law &amp; vſed outward ſacrifices. The ſacrifices &amp; ceremonies of Moſes law, dyd ſo longe indure, tyl y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſtes ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, which was perfigured &amp; ſygni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied before by the Iewes outwarde ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice which was ones fyniſhed and
<pb facs="tcp:8474:38"/> offered. But as ſone as Chriſte had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vp hys ſacryfyce on the Croſſe, whych was to him, as a certayn altare all outwarde ſacryfyces, altares, and oblations was abrogated &amp; put down Neuertheleſſe vnto that tyme he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bad no Sacrifice or oblation ordened by Moyſes to be offered. Chriſte a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the newe teſtament before hys paſſion, was circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed, he came to the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple or Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and cate the Iewes Paſcal la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be after the order of Moyſes law: ſhal we therfore be circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed? ſhal we come to the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? ſhal we be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alſo to eat y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ieues paſchal lambe after the order of Moyſes law? Therfore, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place which ye haue reher? ſed here before, maketh nothing for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tares &amp; oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to be had emong chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſt hath ſuffred hys paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: which was ſo perfyt a ſacrifyce or oblation, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther neded neuer mo after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, to be offred to take ſines away. Ther fore your meſtres miſſa &amp; ye that wyll haue ſtyll both altares and outwarde
<pb facs="tcp:8474:39"/> ſacrifices for ſynnes, are enemyes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſtes moſte holy worde, whyche dothe in many places teſtify, that at a certayne tyme, all outwarde acryfyces ſhoulde haue an ende, and that the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me was, when Chriſte offered him ſelfe a ſufficiente ſacrifice for the redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the whole worlde. To proue thys that I haue ſayde to be true, fyrſte I wyll ſhew by the ſcrypture, that the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feryng vp of ſacryfyces, was no moral precepte, and therfore not euerlaſtyng but a temporall and ceremonyall, too ſerue the infancy and weakenes, of the Iewes a whyle, that is, to the tyme of perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Eſaye in the fyrſt chapter of his prophecy wryteth thus: What ſhal I do wyth your manyfolde ſacryfyces ſayeth the Lorde? The burnte ſacrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of rammes, and the fat of the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes doo I lothe. I loue not the bloude yf oxen, lambes and gotes. When ye ſhal come to appere before me, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyreth it of your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, that ye ſhould treade on my courutes? Brynge youre
<pb facs="tcp:8474:39"/> rewarde nomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>re in vayne. Ieremy al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo wryteth thus in the fyrſte Chapter: Wherfore bryngeſte thou me Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe oute of Stba, and calamus and ambre oute of a farre lande. Youre burned offerynges pleaſe me not, and youre Sacrifyces are not ſwete vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me. God ſayethe alſo in the .v. of Amos theſe wordes: I defye your holy dayes, neyther wyll I ſmell in youre Congregations, and when ye ſhall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyce vnto me burnt offerynges and ſacryfyces of meate, they ſhall not be acceptable vnto me, and I wyl not lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke vpon the offerynges of fattes. O houſe of Iſraell, haue ye offered in the wyldernes for the ſpace of .xl. yeres of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferynges and ſacrifyces vnto me? The ſame ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is wryte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the .xl. Pſlame The ſame matter is conteyned in the Li. Pſalme in theſe wordes: Thou art not delyted in hoſtes or offerynges, or elles I would haue offred. Thou wylt haue no burnt ſacryfyce and hoſtes to be offered, but thes ſacrifices wylt thou
<pb facs="tcp:8474:40"/> not dyſpyſe, a ſorofull ſpyrite, a lowe brought harte &amp; a contritt. Dauid ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion of the ſame mater in the .xl pſalme: Thou loueſt not a ſacrifice and an offeryng of meate, but y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt bored thorow myn eares: thou haſt not requi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rey burnt ſacrifice &amp; hoſtes, to be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp for ſyn, Paul alſo in the .x. chap. of the epiſtle to the Hebrewes wryteth thus, of the abrogation of ceremonies, ſacrifices, and oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the old law: The lawe hauynge a ſhaddow of good thinges of to come: &amp; not beyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſelfe, can neuer make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ar vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, perfit with thy oblations, which it offerethe the very ſame contynually euery yere, or els ſhould offering haue be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> left of becauſe they which had offred vp ſacryfyce, and had therby clenſed &amp; purifyed, ſhoulde haue had fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furth nomore grudge of ſyn in theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcience. But in theſe is a reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſynnes yearly. For the bloud of bulles and gotes ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not take away ſyn. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, when he was obout to come in to
<pb facs="tcp:8474:40"/> the world he ſayd. Thou wouldeſt not haue ſacryfyce and oblation, but thou haſte made fyt a body to me, and thou haſte not allowed burnte Sacryfyces for ſynne: Then ſayde I, here come I, it is wrytten in the begynnynge of the booke of me, that I ſhoulde doo thy wyll (O God) When he ſayeth before. thou wouldeſt not haue ſacrifyce, obla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, and burnte offerynges for ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, neyther dyddeſt thou allowe them that are offered after the maner of the Law: then ſayd he, here am I (O god) to doo thy wyll. He taketh awaye the former, that he maye ſtabliſhe and ſette vp the latter, by the whyche wyll, we are made holye and ſanctyfyed, by the offerynge vp of the bodye of Ieſus Chryſte ones fynyſſhed and donne.</p>
               <p>Nowe oute of theſe places of ſcripture whych I haue reherſed, I gather, that all outwarde oblations, burnt offerin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, ſacryfyces and oblations both of beaſtes and of meat, as of bread &amp; ſuch lyke was quiet abrogated &amp; put down
<pb facs="tcp:8474:41"/> at that tyme, when oure ſauioure Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte offered vp on the Croſſe hys mooſt bleſſed and perfyte ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce, whyche was prefygured and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifyed before longe tyme, by the obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions and ſacryfices nowe put downe and abrogated. Yf that all kyndes of ſacrifices of veſtes and meates be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated by Chryſtes Sacryfyce, we oughte to haue nomore outwarde ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifyces. Then ye meſtres Miſſa wyth youre Chaplaynes, do amiſſe to ſet v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that, whych Chriſt put downe: yea and thoughe Chriſte had not abrogated the offerynge vp of beaſtes &amp; of bread, yet ye doo greuouſly offende God in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge vp a newe kynde of ſacryfyce or wor w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>yppynge of God whyche he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded. Sayeth not almighty God by Eſay the prophete and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that he is falſely worſhypped by the commayndementes of men? And God gyueth a playn commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> .xii. of Deuteronomy ſaiynge.</p>
               <p>Do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou onely that, whyche I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde
<pb facs="tcp:8474:41"/> the: neyther ſhalte thou put any thynge to the commaundemente, neyther take any thinge from it. That God is ſore diſpleaſed with offeringes inuented by man, the death of Nadab and Abiu Leuitici the .x. doth teſtifye, where as they bothe were burnte to deathe, for offerynge vp of ſtrange fyre whyche was not commaunded them. Where haue ye any commaundemente of God that ye ſhoulde offer vp breade in the new Teſtament? ſurely, nowher in the new Teſtamente. Furthermore, maſtres Miſſa ye and your Chaplay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes doo noughtlye, and contrary vnto the ſcriptures, to ſet vp outwarde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tares, when as all outwarde ſacryfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ar abrogated. What ſhould Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes temple doo wyth an outwarde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare where there is no outwarde ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce to be offered vpon it? The ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices that ar allowed only for Chriſten men to be offered, are theſe: The calues of oure lyppes prayers thankes pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng of god, charitablenes, and mercy
<pb facs="tcp:8474:42"/> and almes to the poore, oure awne bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes mortifyed, a contrite harte and a troubled ſpyrit. I pray you now, what ſhall we nede an outwarde and a ſtony altare to offer theſe ſacrifices on? The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when as we nede no ſuche altares it is euyll done of you to holde ſtyll altares in the churche, where as Chriſtes ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhoulde be. Now youre altares do none other good, but bere falſe wytnes agaynſt Chriſt, that he hath not made perfyt all, that are ſanctified, wyth his bleſſed ſacrifice: for an outward altare preſuppoſeth an outwarde Sacryfyce but another outward ſacrifyce for ſyn, after Chriſtes ſacrifyce, preſuppoſeth, that Chriſtes ſacrifyce was not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and perfyt inoughe: For Paule to the Hebrwes proueth, that the ſacrifice that hath another ſucceding, is vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyt. But all ſuch falſe wytnes and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifycations, whych ſygnify any thyng agaynſte Chriſte, oughte to be putte downe and deſtroyed: but it is nowe proued, that the altars whyche are in
<pb facs="tcp:8474:42"/> the churche, preſuppoſe and ſygnyfy agaynſt Chriſte, therfore they oughte to be broken downe and taken awaye. Then ſhall ye my maſters that ar miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaryes, ſaye meſſe wythoute altares: yf ye wyll nedes ſaye Meſſe. I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der oftymes, where is nowe the zeale emonge Chriſten men, whyche was emonge the carnal and ſtubburne Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes. Yf we, whyche woulde be reke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned perfyte Chriſtianes, hadde bene ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elous for the kepynge of the new law as they wer for the olde, as ſoone as we had ſene any altare ſet vp in the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, we woulde haue ſayde vnto them that ſet it vp. What vnfaithfulnes is thys, that ye can not be contente wyth Chryſte, and the lawe of the Goſpell, but ye wyl nedes ſette vp Altares and outwarde Sacryfyces after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Moyſes lawe? Why ſette ye vp agayne Altares and Sacryfyces, whyche oure redemer and Sauioure Chriſt hath put down and abrogated? how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye for ſhame ſet vp altars, when
<pb facs="tcp:8474:43"/> as the chyldren of Iſraell. Ioſue .xxii. coulde not abyde, that the tribe of Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben, Gad and the halfe tribe of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſes, ſhould ſet vp an altare any whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, to doo ſacrifice on, ſauynge only by the tabernacle? and yet they were bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to offer vp ſacrifyces, and to haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tares by the tabernacle. Now haue I proued ſufficiently that contrary vnto the ſcripture, ye offer vp bread, for ſyn and buylde altars in the temples of Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fremouth.</speaker>
               <p>thys do I alſo lay vnto this womans charge, that ſhe wyth her chaplaynes, taketh in hande to offere vp Chriſt agayne, and to take ſynne awaye, wyth the offerynge vp of Chriſt, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he toke ſynne a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he offered hys bleſſed bodye vpon the croſſe, whyche thynge I ſhall proue to be iniurious to Chriſtes paſſyon and preſthode and contrary vnto the word of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porphiry.</speaker>
               <p>Almyghty god ſayde vnto the Ieues: <hi>In cathedra Moſi ſcribe &amp; phariſae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſederunt,</hi> that is, in the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge ſtoole of Moyſes, haue ſytten
<pb facs="tcp:8474:43"/> the ſcribes and the phariſes: do what ſoeuer they byd ye do, but accordynge vnto theyr workes, do ye not, for they ſay, and do not. Yf that the Ieues wer bounde to do that whyche the Scribes and phariſes bad them do, we are now bounde to do in the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thoſe thynges, that our biſſhoppes and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinaries byd vs do: But oure ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries haue commaunded vs &amp; the meſſe to offer vp Chriſt agayne dayly for the takynge awaye of ſynne, therfore we ar bounde to offer vp Chriſte agayne to take ſynnes awaye. And in doynge of oure ſuperiours commaundement, we pleaſe God: who bad vs obeye our ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours. Therfore in offerynge vp Chriſte agayne to releaſe ſynnes, bothe of the quycke and the dead, is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto the wyll of God, but plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt and acceptable vnto him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege.</speaker>
               <p>The Iewes were bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, I grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you, ſo longe to obey the Scribes and phariſees, as they ſat in Moſes chayr, or teachynge ſtoole, but no longer. So
<pb facs="tcp:8474:44"/> So longe ſat they in Moſes teachyng ſtoole or chayre, as they taughte only Moyſes lawe and nothynge of theyr awne: But when as the Scribes and Phariſes taught theyr awn traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, they ſat in theyr awne chayre or teachyng ſtoole, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were the Iewes ſo lytle bound to obey them, that Chriſte gaue them a playne commaundement, that they ſhould not obey the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but auoyde and ſhunne theyr doctrine, and therfore ſayde he Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew. xvi. Beware of the leuyn of the Phariſees, in the whyche place, leuyn, (as the ſcrypture expoundeth it ſelfe) betokeneth the doctryne of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees. Yf that al the Iewes were bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to doo what ſoeuer the Scribes and Phariſees dyd commaunde wythout any exception, whether it were contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſcripture or no, then brake the Apoſtles Chriſtes commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, when as they woulde not waſſhe theyr handes, when they wente to meate, for the Phariſes and the Scribes ſayde
<pb facs="tcp:8474:44"/> vnto Chriſte. Why doo thy dyſciples breake the ordinao<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the elders? for they waſhe not theyr handes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they eate bread: but Chriſt in defendyng of his diſciples, declareth, that they brake not his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement in breakyng of the Phariſees co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: therfore by theſe places of ſcripture, it is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that a man is ſomtyme bounde to obey the Phariſees co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, that is, when they teach nothing but the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſome tyme men ar bounde to diſobey and reſiſt theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that is, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſyt in theyr awn chay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, &amp; teach traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which ar notin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture. The phariſes taught that al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhoulde waſſhe theyr ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des before meat. They taught, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould not ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nor theyr father &amp; mother, but put mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney in the box, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therby they ſhould be excuſed from honoryng of theyr father and mother. No ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſo mad to beleue that by thys ſaiynge of Chriſte: in the chayre of Moſes haue ſytte the ſcribes and phariſes, doo whatſoeuer they dyd
<pb facs="tcp:8474:45"/> you do: men ar bound to kepe the pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees commaundement, when they ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther teache men to waſſhe handes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore meat, or to dyſhonour theyr father and mother. Then can ye not gather of the texte, that we are bounde to obeye oure Byſſhoppes and paſtores in all tradytions and commaundementes, whatſoeuer they commaunde vs to ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe wythoute any exception, but onely in ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, as they haue out of the new Teſtament. Yf that we were bounde to beleue and obeye what ſoeuer the preachers, or ordinaries, or Biſhoppes dyd preache or commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, Certayn Ieues of the ſecte of the pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, whyche had beleued and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Chriſt, ſtert vp and teached the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. Act .xv. that they coulde not be ſaued, excepte they were circumciſed, and kepte the lawe wyth the Goſpell: was the Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that tyme bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to beleue and to obeye theſe preachers commaundementes? Biſſhop Fyſſher layde that the Byſſhop of Rome was
<pb facs="tcp:8474:45"/> heed of the churche. Byſſhop Reps a lytle before the Idole of Walſyngam was put downe, ſayd, that men ſhould go on pylgrymage. Biſſhop Gardiner ſayd, that Images ſhould be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped wyth outwarde worſhyp, and that men were iuſtifyed by theyr workes.</p>
               <p>Theſe .iii. were ordinaries: were al they that wer vnder them at that tyme, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they preached ſuche doctrine, bounde to doo as theſe men ſayde, or they were not? Yf they were not, I praye you tell me, why were they not bounde to obey theyr doctrine and commaundemente?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Philargy.</speaker>
               <p>becauſe they commaunded bothe, that it was not in the ſcripture and alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary doctrine vnto the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fremouth.</speaker>
               <p>Then when as youre ordinary commaundeth you, and your meſtres Miſſa, any thyng concerning reli, gion that is not in the ſcripture, or contrary vnto the ſcripture, ye are not bounde to obeye hym, and kepe hys co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente: But thys commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of your ordinary, where as he
<pb facs="tcp:8474:46"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth you to offer vp chriſt again is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of god in his ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yea it is cleane contrary vnto the ſcripture, wherfore ye ſhould haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more in this caſe haue folowed the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of your ordinary then the good Iewes, kepte the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundemente of the Phariſes, where they taughte men to dyſhonour theyr father and mother.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouuelege.</speaker>
               <p>And I for my parte ſhal proue, that both your kynde of preſthode that offer vp Chriſt agayne, &amp; alſo your maſtres, whom ye haue taken in hande to defende, ar con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary vnto the word of God. They that go aboute to make Chriſtes ſacrifyce vnperfyt, ar enemies vnto the ſcriptur and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary vnto the word of god: but your preiſthode wyth the meſſe, doo ſo: therfore they both ar contrary vnto the ſcripture. Saynt Paule in the epyſtel to the Hebrwes proueth by theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that the ſacrifyces and preiſthod of Moyſes law, are vnperfyt, becauſe they coulde neuer make perfyt them,
<pb facs="tcp:8474:46"/> whyche were vnder the law. And in the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th chapter, he ſayeth thus, ſpeking of the lawe and ſacrifices of Moyſes The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement which we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t before is taken away for the weaknes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profytablenes of it, for the lawe hathe brought nothyng vnto perfection, but it was a leadynge vnto a better hope. The preiſtes of the old law were many becauſe they were not ſuffred by death to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue. But chriſt, becauſe he endu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth for euer, hath an euerlaſting preſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode: wherfore he lyuynge for euer, can perfitly ſaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which thorow him, go vnto god. Marke theſe wordes wel, for they ar not myne but Paules. Paule alſo in the .x. of the epiſtle to the Hebr. proueth that the lawe is vnperfit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it could not, with the ſacrifices &amp; hoſtes which, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſtes offred vp euery yere of freſh make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cam to the law perfit: or els (ſaieth paul) they wold ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue left of offeri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. Of the wordes I ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke thes reſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifices of moſes law wer vnꝑfit, becauſe thei could not make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8474:47"/> perfyte, for whome they were offered, then yf that Chriſtes ſacryfyce make not all them perfyt, for whome it was offered, it was vnperfyt alſo: But ye offer vp agayne for them, for whome Chriſte ones before hathe offered, ergo ye reken, that the ſacrifyce of Chriſte made not them perfyt, and ſo ye reken Chriſt no perfyter a preiſt, then Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes preiſtes were, and hys ſacryfyce no perfiter, then theyr Sacrifices were.</p>
               <p>Marke well the wordes of Paule. <hi>Lex his hoſtiis, quas ſingulis annis continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter offerunt, nun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>quam</ex>
                     </expan> poteſt acced entes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectos reddere, alioqui nonne deſiiſſent offerre?</hi> The law can neuer make them that come vnto it perfyte, wyth theſe ſacrifyces, whyche they offer contynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally euery yere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame: Or els I praye you, hadde not they ceaſed from offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge Ye maye ſe by Paule here, that where as there is no ceaſynge from of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferynge, that there, is no perfection of ſacrifice: but ye offer vp Chriſte again and ceaſe neuer one daye in the yeare,
<pb facs="tcp:8474:47"/> ſauynge one, (yf that ye ceaſe then) from offerynge hym agayne, therfore, ye make as much as lyeth in you, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes Sacrifyce imperfyt. Whoſoeuer maketh Chriſtes ſacrifyce vnperfyt, is blaſphemous to Chriſt, and is a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of Antichryſt: but it it proued, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres Miſſa, that you wyth youre cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playnes doo ſo: ergo ye wyth youre Chaplaynes are Blaſphemous vnto Chriſte, and membres of Antichryſte. That in offerynge vp Chriſte agayne, ye be proude, arrogante, and take more auctorite, then euer God gaue you, I wyll proue it thus. What ſoeuer the hyghe preiſte maye not doo, whyche is bothe God and man, that can not a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple preiſte laufully doo, whyche is but a mere man: But Chriſte oure hyghe preiſt can not offer hym ſelfe vp again then can no ſymple Preiſtes, that are but mere men, offer vp laufully Chriſt agayne: but ye take in hande to doo ſo, therfore it, that ye take in hande, is vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laufull, and ye are in doynge of youre
<pb facs="tcp:8474:48"/> facte, preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptuous and arroga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, taking vnto you more auctorite, then yt haue gyuen vnto you. That Chriſt can not offer vp him ſelfe agayn, theſe wordes of Paule to the Hebrwes .ix. do teſtify. <hi>In ipſum coelum ingreſſus eſt ut appareat nunc in conſpectu dei pro nobis, non ut ſoepius offer at ſemetipſum, quemadmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum pontifex ingreditur in ſancta ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis annis, per ſanguinem alienum: Alioqui oportuiſſet ſaepius paſſum fuiſſe a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dito mundo. etc.</hi> He entred into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen it ſelfe, to appere in the ſyghte of God for vs, not to offer hym ſelfe ofte tymes vp: as the high preiſt entreth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the temple euery yeare by ſtraunge bloud. For then from the begynning of the world, ſhoulde he haue oft ſuffered. Marke ye not here that Paule ſayeth, that Chriſt ſhould haue oft ſuffered, yf he had done a certayn thyng ofte? that ſame thyng was offeryng of hym ſelfe, as the texte dothe expreſſedly declare.</p>
               <p>Then ſeynge that Paule ioyneth inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parably together, ofte offerynge, and
<pb facs="tcp:8474:48"/> ſufferynge: it folowethe well, that ſo oft as Chriſte is offered: ſo oft dothe he ſuffer, and they that make hym to be ofte offered, maketh hym to be ſlayne. But ye maſtres Miſſa wyth your cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playnes, offer Chriſt a thouſand tymes in one yeare, then doo ye kyll Chriſte a thouſande tymes in one yeare. Nowe my Lord iudge, what thys woman de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth for kyllynge of Chriſt ſo oft, I refer it vnto your iudgement.</p>
               <p>Ye ſay alſo maſtres Miſſa, that ye take ſynnes awaye wyth the offerynge vp of Chriſte, and Paule ſayeth: <hi>Abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſanguinis effuſione non fit remiſſio.</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute ſheddynge of bloude, there is no forgyuenes: then it folowethe alſo by this place, that ye &amp; youre chaplaynes ar bloudy ſacrificers. Now to you my maſters y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> be preſtes what chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> biſhop wyl co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund you to offer vp Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to take ſyn away, ſeynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as oft as he is offred vp ſo oft muſt he ſuffer, and haue his bloud ſhed. None ſurely, for they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do ſo, are of the ryght lynage
<pb facs="tcp:8474:49"/> of that Byſſhop, whyche ſayde: <hi>Neceſſe eſt, ut unus moriatur pro populo, ne tota gens pereat:</hi> and of theyrs alſo that ſaid <hi>Nos habemus legem, &amp; ſecundum hanc debet mori.</hi> There muſte one dye for the people, leaſt the hole multitude ſhould peryſhe. We haue a lawe and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to that, he muſte dye.</p>
               <p>Dauid and Paule ſaye, that Chriſt is an euerlaſtynge Preiſte, and hys preiſthode hathe no ende. No man can ſuccede him, that laſteth for euer, chriſt dureth for euer, then can no man ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede hym: then are ye not Chriſtes ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours as ye woulde be taken. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, ſeynge that Chriſtes preiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode is euerlaſtynge there can no other Preiſtehode laufully ſuccede, then is youre Preiſtehode, whyche ye woulde brynge in after Chriſtes preiſtode, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laufull. Yf ye ſaye, that ye are of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ordre, Paule ſhewynge the dyffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwene Chriſtes preiſthode and the preiſthode of Moyſes lawe, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that none ſuche as ye be, can be of
<pb facs="tcp:8474:49"/> Chriſtes order. Theſe .iii. properties. wherby Chriſtes preiſthode dyfferethe from all other preiſthodes. The fyrſt propertie that longeth vnto a Preiſte of Chriſtes order, is to be but one, and wythout ſynne: The ſeconde is, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for euer in hys preiſthode. The thyrde is to offer but ones, and wyth that offeryng to make perfyt all them, for whome he offereth. All theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties are playnly ſet oute in the .vii. and .x. chapters of the epiſtle to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, in theſe wordes. They were made many preiſtes, becauſe they were not ſuffered by death to continue. But thys preiſte, becauſe he abydeth ſtyll, the ſame for euer, hath an euerlaſtynge preiſthode, wherfore he can ſaue fully them, that thorow hym goo vnto God, euer lyuynge for that intente, that he myghte make interce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſyon for them.</p>
               <p>Yt was mete that we had ſuch a hyghe Byſhop, that ſhould be, godly and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout, innocent, vndefyled, ſet a ſyde fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynners, and hygher then the heauens,
<pb facs="tcp:8474:50"/> whyche ſhoulde not haue nede euery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daye to offer vp Sacryfyces as thoſe hyghe preiſtes had: fyrſt for theyr awn ſynnes, and then after, for the ſynnes of the people: For that he dyd ones, when he offered vp him ſelfe, and with one oblation he made perfyte for euer, them that are ſanctifyed: But ye are many preiſtes, and lyue not euer and are not wythoute ſynne, and make not them perfyte, for whome ye offer wyth one oblation: Therfore ar ye not prei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes of Chriſtes order, yea neyther of his order, nor ordynaunce, for he neuer ordyned any kynde of preiſtes wherof he hath made no mention in hys ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>A preiſte whych is ordened of God, to offer vp alone wythout any felowes in office, an euerlaſtynge offeryng for the takyngt awaye of ſynne, and dothe hys deuty perfytly, hath great wronge done vnto hym, yf any man take hys office in hande or wyll ioyne hym ſelfe in offyce wyth hym, wythout his leaue
<pb facs="tcp:8474:50"/> or commaundemente: Chriſte was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned of God to offer alone wythout any felowes in offyce, an euerlaſtynge oblation, for the releſyng of ſynne, and that offyce doth he perfytly, yet ye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent for, and wythout lycence, thruſte your ſelues into Chriſtes offyce, to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer wyth hym, for the takynge awaye of ſynnes. Therfore ye do Chriſt playn wronge, and not onely hym, but alſo hys father, who ſente hym. Now, howe can this preiſthode of youres be of god whyche is iniurius and doth wronge, bothe to the Father of heauen, and to Chriſte hys ſonne, and oure redemer? Then yf the Meſſe leane vpon youre preiſthode, they muſte bothe fall togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Here haue I proued alſo that this Meſſe is not ordened of God, and that ſhe is contrary to the ſcrypture, and a blaſphemous me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of Antichryſt, and iniurious vnto the preiſthod of Chriſt and to hys paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo, and a foule ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latres, and a cauſer of Idolatry. Whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſuche an Idolatres oughte to be
<pb facs="tcp:8474:51"/> holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtyll in Chriſtes church for god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſeruyce or no, I refer all the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vnto you, my Lorde Iudge, whych haue auctorite in thys matter to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myn as ye haue ſe euydence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Palemon.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe men thy accuſers, haue brought furth ſufficyent euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; wytnes, that thou arte not of God, that thou art co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and enemy vnto the holy ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and and Idolatres, makynge a god of vnconſecrated bread and wyne, and that to the greate iniury of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes paſſion thou offereſt vp Chriſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, and as muche as lyeth in the, kylleſt hym a thouſande tymes in one yeare. Wherfore, thou haſt deſerued deathe, and art worthye to be burned.</p>
               <p>But leaſte thy fathers generation the Papiſtes ſhoulde ſaye, that we are as deſyrous of bloude ſheddyng, as they were, when they bare the ſwynge, I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde the in payne of burnynge to packe the out of thys realme, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all thy bagges &amp; baggage w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in theſe. viii. da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes, &amp; go to thy father the pope, with al
<pb facs="tcp:8474:51"/> the ſpede, that thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt, &amp; ſay, that her is in Englande no more place for hym neyther for any of hys generation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>knouu.</speaker>
               <p>Syr, yf it pleaſe you, yf ther be no man appoynted to ſe thys woman ſhypped, and conueyed out of the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, the Preiſtes, wyll kepe her ſtyl in theyr chambers and wyll abuſe her, as they haue done before: Therfore, yf youre Lordſhyp wyll let me haue her in my cuſtody, I ſhall ſe her conueyed ones vnto the ſea, let her chuſe her, whether ſhe wyll come agayne or no.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</speaker>
               <p>I am content, ſaye not wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man but thou art warned: yf that thou euer come into thys realme agayn, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thes .viii. dayes loke none other but to be ſerued eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thy father hath ſerued oure brethren in tyme paſt.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:8474:52"/>
            <head>The Meſſe ſpeaketh</head>
            <l>Helpe and defende my good brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all</l>
            <l>Whych loue doctrine Cathedrall</l>
            <l>And do beleue vnwryten veritie</l>
            <l>To be as good as ſcriptures ſincerite</l>
            <l>Becauſe in the Bible I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de</l>
            <l>The Heretikes woulde burye me vnder the grounde</l>
            <l>I praye you hartely yf it be poſſible</l>
            <l>To get my a place in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great Bible</l>
            <l>Or elſe as I do vnderſtande</l>
            <l>I ſhalbe baniſhed out of thys la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de</l>
            <l>And ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled with ſorow &amp; payn</l>
            <l>To returne to Rome to my father agayne</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:8474:52"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
